<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Constitutio[ns] and canons ecclesiasticall treated vpon by the Bishop of London, president of the conuocation for the prouince of Canterbury, and the rest of the bishops and clergie of the said prouince: and agreed vpon with the Kings Maiesties licence in their synode begun at London anno Dom. 1603. And in the yeere of the raigne of our soueraigne Lord Iames by the grace of God King of England, France and Ireland the first, and of Scotland the 37. And now published for the due obseruation of them by his Maiesties authoritie, vnder the great Seale of England.</title>
            <title>Constitutions and canons. 1603. English</title>
            <author>Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 175 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72019</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10070.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124736</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898765</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898765</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152063</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72019)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152063)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2005:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Constitutio[ns] and canons ecclesiasticall treated vpon by the Bishop of London, president of the conuocation for the prouince of Canterbury, and the rest of the bishops and clergie of the said prouince: and agreed vpon with the Kings Maiesties licence in their synode begun at London anno Dom. 1603. And in the yeere of the raigne of our soueraigne Lord Iames by the grace of God King of England, France and Ireland the first, and of Scotland the 37. And now published for the due obseruation of them by his Maiesties authoritie, vnder the great Seale of England.</title>
                  <title>Constitutions and canons. 1603. English</title>
                  <author>Church of England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[176] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Robert Barker, printer to the Kings most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno 1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Constitutiones sive canones ecclesiastici.</note>
                  <note>Caption title from p. [27] of text.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-Y⁴.</note>
                  <note>This edition has D1r catchword "Ecclesiasticall"; line 4 of caption title on same page ends "and". A-C4 is partly reset from 10070.3.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ecclesiastical law --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:152063:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152063:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <list>
               <head>Of the Church of England.</head>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Kings ſupremacie ouer the Church <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> of England, in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall to be maintained.</item>
               <item>Impugners of the Kings Supremacie cenſured.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               </item>
               <item>The Church of England a true and Apostolicall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Church.</item>
               <item>Impugners of the publike worſhip of God eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> in the Church of England cenſured.</item>
               <item>Impugners of the Articles of Religion eſtabliſhed <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> in the Church of England cenſured.</item>
               <item>Impugners of the Rites and Ceremonies eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> in the Church of England cenſured.</item>
               <item>Impugners of the gouernement of the Church of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> England by Archbiſhops, Biſhops, &amp;c. cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured.</item>
               <item>Impugners of the forme of conſecrating and orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Archbiſhops, Biſhops, &amp;c. in the Church of England cenſured.</item>
               <item>Authors of Schiſme in the Church of England,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> cenſured.</item>
               <item>Maintainers of Schiſmatickes in the Church of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> England, cenſured.
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:2"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:2"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:3"/>Maintainers of Conuenticles, cenſured.</item>
               <item>Maintainers of Conſtitutions made in Conuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, cenſured.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>¶ Of Diuine Seruice and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments.</head>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ve celebration of Sundayes &amp; Holy daies.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> The preſcript forme of Diuine Seruice to be vſed on Sundayes and Holy dayes.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> The Letanie to bee read on Wedneſdayes and Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> Colledges to vſe the preſcript forme of Diuine Seruice.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> Students in Colledges to weare Surpliſses, in time of Diuine Seruice.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> Reuerence and attention to bee vſed within the Church in time of Diuine Seruice.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> Loyterers not to bee ſuffered neere the Church in time of Diuine Seruice.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> Bread and VVine to bee prouided againſt euery Communion.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> The Communion to be thrice a yeere receiued.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> VVarning to be giuen beforehand for the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.
<pb facs="tcp:152063:3"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:4"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>Students in alledges to receiue the Communion <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> foure times a yeere.</item>
               <item>Copes to be worne in Cathedral Churches by thoſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> that adminiſter the Communion.</item>
               <item>Surpliſſes and Hoods to bee worne in Cathedrall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> Churches when there is no Communion.</item>
               <item>Notorious offendours not to bee admitted to the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> Communion.</item>
               <item>Schiſmaticks not to bee admitted to the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/>
               </item>
               <item>Strangers not to bee admitted to the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/>
               </item>
               <item>Fathers not to be Godfathers in Baptiſme, nor <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> children not Communicants.</item>
               <item>The lawfull vſe of the Croſſe in Baptiſme <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>¶ Miniſters their Ordination, Function, and Charge.</head>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oure ſolemne times appointed for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="31"/> of Ministers.</item>
               <item>None to bee made Deacon and Miniſter, both in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="32"/> one day.</item>
               <item>The Titles of ſuch as are to be made Miniſters.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="33"/>
               </item>
               <item>The qualitie of ſuch as are to be made Miniſters.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="34"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="35"/> The examination of ſuch as are to be made Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="36"/> Subſcription required of ſuch as are to bee made Miniſters.
<list>
                     <item>The Articles of Subſcription.</item>
                     <item>The forme of Subſcription.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="37"/> Subſcription before the Dioceſan.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="38"/> Reuolters after Subſcription, cenſured.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="39"/> Cautions for institution of Miniſters into Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="40"/> An oath against Symonie at institution into Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="41"/> Licences for pluralitie of Benefices limited, and Reſidence enioyned.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="42"/> Reſidence of Deanes in their Churches.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="43"/> Deanes and Prebendaries to Preach during their Reſidence.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="44"/> Prebendaries to be reſident vpon their Benefices.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="45"/> Beneficed Preachers being reſident vpon their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings to preach euery Sunday.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="46"/> Beneficed men not Preachers to procure moneth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sermons.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="47"/> Abſence of Beneficed men to be ſupplied by Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates that are allowed Preachers.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="48"/> None to be Curats but allowed by the Biſhop.
<pb facs="tcp:152063:5"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:6"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:6"/>Miniſters not allowed Preachers, may not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound.</item>
               <item>Strangers not admitted to Preach without ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="50"/> their Licence.</item>
               <item>Strangers not admitted to preach in Cathedrall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="51"/> Churches without ſufficient authoritie.</item>
               <item>The names of ſtrange Preachers to bee noted in a <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="52"/> Booke.</item>
               <item>No publike oppoſition betweene Preachers.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="53"/>
               </item>
               <item>The Licences of Preachers refuſing Conformitie,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="54"/> to be voyd.</item>
               <item>The forme of a Prayer to bee vſed by Preachers <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="55"/> before their Sermons.</item>
               <item>Preachers and Lecturers to reade diuine Seruice <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="56"/> and adminiſter the Sacraments twiſe a yeere at the leaſt.</item>
               <item>The Sacraments not to bee refuſed at the hands of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="57"/> vnpreaching Miniſters.</item>
               <item>Miniſters reading Diuine Seruice, and Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="58"/> the Sacraments, to weare Surpliſſes, and Graduats therewithall, Hoods.</item>
               <item>Miniſters to Catechize euery Sunday.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="59"/>
               </item>
               <item>Confirmation to bee perfourmed once in three <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="60"/> yeeres.</item>
               <item>Miniſters to prepare children for Confirmation.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="61"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:7"/>Miniſters not to marrie any perſons without Bannes or Licence.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="63"/> Miniſters of exempt Churches not to marry with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Bannes or Licence.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="64"/> Ministers ſolemnly to bid Holy dayes.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="65"/> Ministers ſolemnly to denounce Recuſants and Excommunicats.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="66"/> Ministers to conferre with Recuſants.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="67"/> Miniſters to viſite the ſicke.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="68"/> Miniſters not to refuſe to chriſten or bury.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="69"/> Miniſters not to deferre Chriſtening, if the childe be in danger.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="70"/> Ministers to keepe a Regiſter of Chriſtnings, Weddings, and Burials.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="71"/> Miniſters not to Preach or adminiſter the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in priuate houſes.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="72"/> Ministers not to appoint publike or priuate Faſts, or Propheſies, or to exorcize, but by authority.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="73"/> Ministers not to hold priuate Conuenticles.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="74"/> Decencie in apparell enioyned to Miniſters.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="75"/> Sober conuerſation required in Ministers.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="76"/> Ministers at no time to forſake their Calling.
<pb facs="tcp:152063:7"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:8"/>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:8"/>
               <head>¶ Schoolemaſters.</head>
               <item>NOne to teach Schoole without Licence.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="77"/>
               </item>
               <item>Curats deſirous to Teach, to bee licenced be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="78"/> others.</item>
               <item>The duetie of Schoolemasters.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="79"/>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>¶ Things appertaining to Churches.</head>
               <item>THE great Bible and Booke of Common <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="80"/> prayer to be had in euery Church.</item>
               <item>A Font of ſtone for Baptiſme in euery <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="81"/> Church.</item>
               <item>A decent Communion Table in euery Church.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="82"/>
               </item>
               <item>A Pulpit to be prouided in euery Church.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="83"/>
               </item>
               <item>A Cheſt for Almes in euery Church.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="84"/>
               </item>
               <item>Churches to be kept in ſufficient reparations.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="85"/>
               </item>
               <item>Churches to be ſuruayed, and the decayes certified <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="86"/> to the high Commiſsioners.</item>
               <item>A Terrier of Glebelands and other Poſſeſsions <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="87"/> belonging to Churches.</item>
               <item>Churches not to be prophaned.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="88"/>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>¶Churchwardens, Queſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Sidemen.</head>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="89"/> THe choiſe of Churchwardens, and their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="90"/> The choiſe of Sidemen, and their ioynt Office with Churchwardens.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>¶ Pariſh Clearks.</head>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="91"/> PAriſh Clearkes to bee choſen by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>¶ Eccleſiaſticall Courts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Archbiſhops Iuriſdiction.</head>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="92"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>One to be Cited into diuers Courts for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate of the ſame Will.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="93"/> The Rate of <hi>Bona notabilia</hi> liable to the Prerogatiue Court.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="94"/> None to be Cited into the Arches or Audience but dwellers within the Archbiſhops Dioceſſe, or Peculiars.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="95"/> The reſtraint of double Quarrels.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="96"/> Inhibitions not to be granted without the ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an Aduocate.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="97"/> Inhibitions not to be graunted vntill the Appeale
<pb facs="tcp:152063:9"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:10"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:10"/>
be exhibited to the Iudge.</item>
               <item>Inhibitions not to bee granted to factious Appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="98"/> vnleſſe they first ſubſcribe.</item>
               <item>None to marrie within the degrees prohibited.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="99"/>
               </item>
               <item>None to marrie vnder xxj yeeres, without their <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="100"/> Parents conſent.</item>
               <item>By whom Licences to marrie without Bannes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="101"/> ſhalbe granted, and to what ſort of perſons.</item>
               <item>Securitie to bee taken at the granting of ſuch Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cences,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="102"/> and vnder what conditions.</item>
               <item>Oathes to be taken for the Conditions.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="103"/>
               </item>
               <item>An exception for thoſe that are in Widowhood.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="104"/>
               </item>
               <item>No Sentence for Diuorce to bee giuen vpon the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="105"/> ſole confeſsion of the parties.</item>
               <item>No Sentence for Diuorce to be giuen but in open <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="106"/> Court.</item>
               <item>In all Sentences for Diuorce, bond to be taken for <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="107"/> not marrying, during each others life.</item>
               <item>The penaltie for Iudges offending in the premiſſes.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="108"/>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>¶ Eccleſiaſticall Courts belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to Biſhops and inferior Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and the proceedings in them.</head>
               <item>NOtorious crimes and ſcandals to be certified <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="109"/> into Eccleſiastical Courts by preſentment.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:11"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="110"/> Schiſmatickes to be preſented.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="111"/> Diſturbers of diuine Seruice to be preſented.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="112"/> Not Communicants at Eaſter to be preſented.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="113"/> Miniſters may preſent.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="114"/> Ministers ſhall preſent Recuſants.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="115"/> Ministers and Churchwardens not to bee ſued for preſenting.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="116"/> Churchwardens not bound to preſent oftner then twice a yeere.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="117"/> Churchwardens not to be troubled for not preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting oftner then twice a yeere.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="118"/> The olde Churchwardens to make their preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, before the new be ſworne.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="119"/> Conuenient time to bee aſsigned for framing Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="120"/> None to bee Cited into Eccleſiasticall Courts by Proceſſe of <hi>Quorum nomina.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="121"/> None to be cited into ſeueral Courts for one crime.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="122"/> No ſentence of Depriuation or Depoſition to bee pronounced against a Minister, but by the Biſhop.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="123"/> No Acte to be ſped but in open Court.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="124"/> No Court to haue more then one Seale.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="125"/> Conuenient places to bee choſen for the keeping of Courts.
<pb facs="tcp:152063:11"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:12"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:12"/>Peculier and inferior Courts to exhibite the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall copies of Wills into the Biſhops Registry.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>¶ Iudges of Eccleſiaſticall Courts.</head>
               <item>THe Qualitie and oath of Iudges.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="127"/>
               </item>
               <item>The Qualitie of Surrogats.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="128"/>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>¶ Proctors.</head>
               <item>PRoctors not to retaine Cauſes, without the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="129"/> lawfull aſsignement of the parties.</item>
               <item>Proctors not to retaine Cauſes without the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="130"/> of an Aduocate.</item>
               <item>Proctors not to conclude in any Cauſe without <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="131"/> the knowledge of an Aduocate.</item>
               <item>Proctors prohibited the oath <hi>In animam Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="132"/> ſui.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Proctors not to be clamorous in Court.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="133"/>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>¶ Regiſters.</head>
               <item>A Buſes to be reformed in Registers.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="134"/>
               </item>
               <item>A certaine rate of Fees due to all Eccleſiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="135"/> Officers.</item>
               <item>A Table of the rates of Fees to be ſet vp in Courts <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="136"/> and Registries.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:13"/>The whole Fees for ſhewing Letters of Orders and other Licences, due but once in euery Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops time.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>¶ Apparitors.</head>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="138"/>
                  <hi>THE</hi> number of Apparitors restrained.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>¶ Authoritie of Synods.</head>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="139"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Nationall Synode the Church repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="140"/> Synods conclude aſwell the abſent, as the preſent.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="141"/> Deprauers of the Synode cenſured.
<pb facs="tcp:152063:13"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:14"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:152063:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <figure/>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>AMES</hi> by the grace of God King of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> defender of the faith &amp;c.</signed> 
               <salute>To all to whom theſe preſents ſhall come, Greeting.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Whereas our
<pb facs="tcp:152063:15"/>
Biſhops, Deanes of our Cathedrall Churches, Archdeacons, Chapters and Colleges, &amp; the other Cleargie of euery Dioceſſe within the Prouince of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> being ſummoned &amp; called by vertue of our Writ directed to the moſt reuerend father in God <hi>IOHN</hi> late Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring date the <hi>31.</hi> day of Ianuary in the first yeere of our Raigne of <hi>England, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> the <hi>37.</hi> to haue appeared before him in our Cathedrall Church of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in London the <hi>20.</hi> day of March then next enſuing, or elſewhere, as he ſhould haue thought it moſt conuenient, to treat, conſent, and conclude vpon certaine difficult, and vrgent affaires mentioned in the ſaid Writte, Did thereupon at the time appointed, and
<pb facs="tcp:152063:15"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:16"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
within the Cathedrall Church of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> aforeſaid, aſſemble themſelues and appeare in Conuocation for that purpoſe, according to our ſaid Writte before the Right reuerend Father in God <hi>Richard</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> duely (vpon a ſecond Writte of Ours dated the <hi>9.</hi> day of March aforeſaid) authorized, appointed and conſtituted, by reaſon of the ſaide Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> his death, Preſident of the ſaid Conuocation, to execute thoſe things which by vertue of our firſt Writ did appertaine to him the ſaid Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop to haue executed if he had liued: <hi>Wee</hi> for diuers vrgent and weighty cauſes and conſiderations vs thereunto eſpecially mouing, of our eſpecial grace, certaine knowledge, and meere motion, did by vertue of our Prerogatiue royal
<pb facs="tcp:152063:17"/>
and ſupreme Authoritie in cauſes Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical, giue and grant by our ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Letters Patents vnder our great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> the one dated the <hi>12.</hi> day of April last past, and the other the <hi>25.</hi> day of Iune then next follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, full, free, and lawfull libertie, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, power, and Authoritie vnto the ſaid Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> Preſident of the ſaid Conuocation, and to the other Biſhops, Deanes, Archdeacons, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Colleges, and the rest of the Cleargie before mentioned of the ſaid Prouince, That they from time to time during our first Parliament now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogued, might conferre, treate, debate, conſider, conſult, and agree of, and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch Canons, Orders, Ordinances and Conſtitutions, as they ſhould thinke neceſſary, fit, &amp; conuenient for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb facs="tcp:152063:17"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:18"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and ſeruice of Almighty God, the good and quiet of the Church, and the better gouernement thereof to be from time to time obſerued, perfourmed, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled and kept aſwel by the Archbiſhops of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the Biſhops &amp; their Succeſſours, and the reſt of the whole Clergie of the ſayd Prouince of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi> in their ſeveral Callings, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, Functions, Miniſteries, Degrees and adminiſtrations, as alſo by all and euery Deane of the Arches, and other Iudge of the ſayd Archbiſhops Courts, Gardians of Spiritualties, Chancellors, Deanes and Chapters, Archdeacons, Commiſſaries, Officials, Regiſters, and all and euery other Eccleſiaſticall Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and their inferiour Miniſters whatſoeuer of the ſame Prouince of <hi>Canterburie</hi> in their and euery of
<pb facs="tcp:152063:19"/>
their diſtinct Courts, and in the order and maner of their and euery of their proceedings: and by all other perſons mthin this Realme, as farre as lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly being members of the Church, it may concerne them, as in our ſayd Letters Patents amongst other clauſes more at large doth appeare. Foraſmuch as the ſayd Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> Preſident of the ſayd Conuocation, and others the ſayd Biſhops, Deanes, Archdeacons, Chapters and Colledges, with the reſt of the Clergie hauing met together at the time and place before mentioned, and then and there by vertue of our ſaid authority granted vnto them, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of, concluded, and agreed vpon cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Canons, Orders, Ordinances and Conſtitutions, to the end and purpoſe by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s limited and preſcribed vnto them,
<pb facs="tcp:152063:19"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:20"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and haue thereupon offred and preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſame vnto <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, moſt humbly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s to giue our Royal aſſent vnto their ſayd Canons, Orders, Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Conſtitutions, according to the forme of a certaine Statute or Acte of Parliament made in that behalfe in the xxv. yeere of the Reigne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, and by our ſayd Prerogatiue Royall, and ſupreme Authority in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall, to rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie by our Letters Patents vnder our great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the ſame: the title and tenour of them being word for word as enſueth:
<pb facs="tcp:152063:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:23"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:23"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:24"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:24"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:25"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:25"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:26"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:26"/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:152063:27"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152063:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Conſtitutions and Canons Eccleſiaſticall treated vpon by the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> Preſident of the Conuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation for the Prouince of Canterbury, and the reſt of the Biſhops and Cleargie of the ſaid Prouince: and agreed vpon with the Kings Maieſties licence in their Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>node begun at London An.Dom.1603.</head>
            <head type="sub">And in the yeere of the raigne of our Soueraigne Lord Iames by the grace of God, King of England, France, and Ireland the firſt, and of Scotland the 37.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>Of the Church of England.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>I.</hi> The Kings ſupremacie ouer the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall, to be maintained.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S our duety to the Kings moſt Excellent Maieſtie requireth, wee firſt decree and ordaine, That the Archbiſhop of Can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terbury (from time to time) all Biſhops of this prouince, all Deanes, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons, Parſons, Vicars, and all other
<pb facs="tcp:152063:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Eccleſiaſticall perſons, ſhall faithfully keepe and obſerue, and (as much as in them lieth) ſhall cauſe to bee obſerued and kept of others, all and ſinguler Lawes and ſtatutes made for reſtoring to the Crowne of this kingdome, the ancient Iuriſdiction ouer the ſtate Eccleſiaſtical, and aboliſhing of all forren power-repugnant to the ſame. Furthermore, al Eccleſiaſtical perſons hauing cure of ſoules, and all other Preachers, and Readers of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie lectures, ſhall to the vttermoſt of their wit, knowledge, and learning, purely and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely (without any colour or diſsimulation) teach, manifeſt, open, and declare foure times euery yeere (at the leaſt) in their Sermons and other Collations and lectures, That all vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and forren power, (foraſmuch as the ſame hath no eſtabliſhment nor ground by the law of God) is for moſt iuſt cauſes taken away and aboliſhed: and that therefore no maner of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, or ſubiection within his Maieſties Realmes and Dominions, is due vnto any ſuch forren power: but that the Kings power with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his Realmes of England, Scotland and Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and all other his Dominions and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys,
<pb facs="tcp:152063:28"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:29"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
is the higheſt power vnder God, to whom all men, aſwell inhabitants, as borne within the ſame, do by Gods Lawes owe moſt loyalty and obedience, afore and aboue all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Powers and Potentates in earth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>II.</hi> Impugners of the Kings ſupremacie cenſured.</head>
                  <p>WHoſoeuer ſhal hereafter affirme that the Kings Maieſty hath not the ſame authority in cauſes Eccleſiaſtical that the godly Kings had amongſt the Iewes, and Chriſtian Emperors in the Primitiue Church, or impeach in any part his Regall ſupremacie in the ſaid cauſes reſtored to the Crowne, and by the Lawes of this Realme therein eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, let him bee excommunicated <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> and not reſtored but only by the Archbiſhop after his repentance and publike reuocation of thoſe his wicked errours.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>III.</hi> The Church of England a true and Apoſtolicall Church.</head>
                  <p>WHoſoeuer ſhall hereafter affirme, that the Church of England by Lawe eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed
<pb facs="tcp:152063:30"/>
vnder the Kings Maieſtie, is not a true and an Apoſtolical Church, teaching &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the doctrine of the Apoſtles, let him be excommunicated <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> and not reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but onely by the Archbiſhop after his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and publike reuocation of this his wicked errour.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>IIII.</hi> Impugners of the publike worſhip of God, eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the Church of England cenſured.</head>
                  <p>WHoſoeuer ſhall herafter affirme that the forme of Gods worſhip in the Church of England, eſtabliſhed by Law and conteined in the booke of Common Prayer, and adminiſtration of Sacraments, is a corrupt, ſuperſtitious, or vnlawfull worſhip of God, or containeth any thing in it that is repugnant to the Scriptures: let him be excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> and not reſtored but by the Biſhop of the place, or Archbiſhop, after his repentance and publike reuocation of ſuch his wicked errors.
<pb facs="tcp:152063:30"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:31"/>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:31"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>V.</hi> Impugners of the Articles of Religion eſtabliſhed in the Church of England cenſured.</head>
                  <p>WHoſoeuer ſhall hereafter affirme that any of the nine and thirtie Articles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed vpon by the Archbiſhops, and Biſhops of both Prouinces, and the whole Cleargy in the Conuocation holden at LON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DON, in the yeere of our Lorde God, one thouſand fiue hundred ſixty two, for the auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of diuerſities of opinions, and for the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of conſent touching true Religion, are in any part ſuperſtitious or erroneous, or ſuch as hee may not with a good conſcience ſubſcribe vnto: let him bee excommunicated <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> and not reſtored, but onely by the Archbiſhop, after his repentance and publike reuocation of ſuch his wicked errors.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>VI.</hi> Impugners of the Rites and Ceremonies eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the Church of England cenſured.</head>
                  <p>WHoſoeuer ſhal hereafter affirme, that the Rites and Ceremonies of the Church of England by Law eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, are wicked, Antichriſtian, or ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<pb facs="tcp:152063:32"/>
or ſuch as beeing commanded by lawfull authoritie, men who are zealouſly and godly affected, may not with any good conſcience approue them, vſe them, or as occaſion requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſubſcribe vnto them: let him bee excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> and not reſtored, vntill he repent and publikely reuoke ſuch his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked errours.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>VII.</hi> Impugners of the gouernment of the Church of England by Archbiſhops, Biſhops, &amp;c. cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured.</head>
                  <p>WHoſoeuer ſhal hereafter affirme, that the gouernement of the Church of England, vnder his Maieſty by Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, Biſhops, Deanes, Archdeacons, and the reſt that beare office in the ſame, is Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian or repugnant to the word of God: let him be excommunicated <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue vntill he repent and publikely reuoke ſuch his wicked errors.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>VIII.</hi> Impugners of the forme of conſecrating and orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:152063:32"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:33"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:33"/>
Archbiſhops, Biſhops, &amp;c. in the Church of England cenſured.</head>
                  <p>WHoſoeuer ſhall hereafter affirme or teach, that the fourme and maner of making and conſecrating Biſhops, Prieſts, or Deacons, conteineth any thing in it, that is repugnant to the word of God, or that they who are made Biſhops, Prieſtes, or Deacons in that forme are not lawfully made, nor ought to be accounted either by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues or by others, to be truly either Biſhops, Prieſts, or Deacons, vntil they haue ſome other calling to thoſe diuine Offices: let him bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> not to bee reſtored vntill he repent and publikely reuoke ſuch his wicked errours.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>IX.</hi> Authours of Schiſme in the Church of England cenſured.</head>
                  <p>WHoſoeuer ſhall hereafter ſeparate themſelues from the Communion of Saints as it is approoued by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles rules, in the Church of England, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine themſelues together in a new brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, accounting the Chriſtians who are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable
<pb facs="tcp:152063:34"/>
to the Doctrine, Gouernment, Rites, and Ceremonies of the Church of England, to be prophane and vnmeete for them to ioyne with in Chriſtian profeſsion: let them bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> and not reſtored, but by the Archbiſhop, after their repentance and publike reuocation of ſuch their wicked er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>X.</hi> Maintainers of Schiſmatickes in the Church of England cenſured.</head>
                  <p>WHoſoeuer ſhall heerafter affirme, That ſuch Miniſters as refuſe to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to the forme and maner of Gods worſhip in the Church of England pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the Communion Booke, and their adherents, may truly take vnto them the name of another Church not eſtabliſhed by Lawe, and dare preſume to publiſh it, that this their pretended Church hath of long time groaned vnder the burden of certaine grieuances im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed vpon it, and vpon the members thereof before mentioned by the Church of England, and the Orders and Conſtitutions therein by Law eſtabliſhed: Let them be excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb facs="tcp:152063:34"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:35"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:35"/>
and not reſtored vntill they repent and publikely reuoke ſuch their wicked errors.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XI.</hi> Maintainers of Conuenticles cenſured.</head>
                  <p>WHoſoeuer ſhall hereafter affirme or maintaine, That there are within this Realme other meetings, aſſemblies or congregations of the Kings borne Subiects, then ſuch as by the lawes of this land are held and allowed, which may rightly challenge to themſelues the name of true and lawful Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: let him be excommunicated and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored but by the Archbiſhop, after his repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and publike reuocation of ſuch his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked errors.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XII.</hi> Maintainers of Conſtitutions made in Conuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, cenſured.</head>
                  <p>WHoſoeuer ſhal hereafter affirme that it is lawfull for any ſort of Miniſters and Lay perſons, or either of them to ioyne together, and make Rules, Orders, or Conſtitutions in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall without the Kings authoritie, and ſhall ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be ruled and gouerned by them: let
<pb facs="tcp:152063:36"/>
them be excommunicated <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> and not be reſtored vntill they repent, and publikely reuoke thoſe their wicked and Anabaptiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call errors.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of diuine Seruice, and <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Sacraments.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="13" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XIII.</hi> Due celebration of Sundayes and Holy dayes.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll maner of perſons within the Church of England ſhall from henceforth celebrate and keepe the Lords day, commonly called Sunday, and other Holy dayes according to Gods holy will and pleaſure, and the Orders of the Church of England preſcribed in that behalfe: that is, in hearing the word of God read and taught, in priuate and publike pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: in acknowledging their offences to God, and amendement of the ſame, in reconciling themſelues charitably to their neighbours where diſpleaſure hath bene, in oftentimes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the Communion of the body &amp; blood
<pb facs="tcp:152063:36"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:37"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:37"/>
of Chriſt, in viſiting of the poore and ſicke, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all godly and ſober conuerſation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XIIII.</hi> The preſcript forme of Diuine Seruice to bee vſed on Sundayes and Holy dayes.</head>
                  <p>THe Common prayer ſhalbe ſaid or ſung diſtinctly and reuerently vpon ſuch daies as are appointed to be kept holy by the Booke of Common prayer, and their Eeues, and at conuenient and vſuall times of thoſe daies, and in ſuch place of euery Church as the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, or Eccleſiaſticall Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary of the place ſhall thinke meete for the largeneſſe or ſtraitneſſe of the ſame, ſo as the people may bee moſt edified. All Miniſters likewiſe ſhall obſerue the Orders, Rites, and Ceremonies preſcribed in the Booke of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer, aſwell in reading the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and ſaying of prayers, as in adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sacraments, without either dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing in regard of preaching, or in any other reſpect, or adding any thing in the matter or forme thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:38"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>XV.</hi> The Letanie to bee read on Wedneſdayes and Fridayes.</head>
                  <p>THe Letany ſhalbe ſaid or ſung when, and as it is ſet downe in the Booke of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer, by the Parſons, Vicars, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, or Curats in all Cathedrall, Collegiat, Pariſh Churches and Chappels, in ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient place, according to the diſcretion of the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, or Eccleſiaſticall Ordinarie of the place. And that wee may ſpeake more particularly, vpon Wedneſdayes and Fridayes weekely, though they bee not Holy dayes, the Miniſter at the accuſtomed houres of Seruice, ſhall reſort to the Church and Chappel, and warning being giuen to the people by tolling of a Bell, ſhall ſay the Leta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie preſcribed in the Booke of Common pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: whereunto wee wiſh euery Houſholder dwelling within halfe a mile of the Church, to come or ſend one at the leaſt of his Houſhold fit to ioyne with the Miniſter in prayers.
<pb facs="tcp:152063:38"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:39"/>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:39"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>XVI.</hi> Colledges to vſe the preſcript forme of Diuine Seruice.</head>
                  <p>IN the whole Diuine Seruice, and Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the holy Communion, in all Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges and Halles in both Vniuerſities, the Order, Forme, and Ceremonies ſhall be duely obſerued as they are ſet downe and preſcribed in the booke of Common prayer, without any omiſsion or alteration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XVII.</hi> Students in Colledges to weare Surpliſses, in time of Diuine Seruice.</head>
                  <p>ALl Maſters and Fellowes of Colledges or Halles, and al the Schollers and Students in either of the Vniuerſities, ſhall in their Churches and Chappels vpon all Sundayes, Holy dayes, and their Eues, at the time of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Seruice weare Surpliſſes, according to the order of the Church of England: and ſuch as are Graduats ſhall agreeably were with their Surpliſſes, ſuch Hoods as doe ſeuerally apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to their Degrees.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>XVIII.</hi> A reuerence and attention to bee vſed within the Church in time of Diuine Seruice.</head>
                  <p>IN the time of Diuine Seruice, and of euery part thereof, all due reuerence is to be vſed: For it is according to the Apoſtles Rule: <hi>Let all things bee done decently, and according to Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi> Anſwerable to which Decencie and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, We iudge theſe our directions following: No man ſhall couer his head in the Church or Chappel in the time of Diuine Seruice, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he haue ſome infirmitie. In which caſe let him weare a Nightcap or Coife. All ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of perſons then preſent ſhall reuerently kneele vpon their knees when the Generall Confeſsion, Letanie, and other Prayers are read, and ſhall ſtand vp at the ſaying of the Beleefe, according to the Rules in that behalfe preſcribed in the Booke of Common Prayer. And likewiſe when in time of Diuine Seruice the Lord IESVS ſhalbe mentioned, due and lowly reuerence ſhall bee done by all perſons preſent as it hath bene accuſtomed: teſtifying by theſe outward Ceremonies and geſtures, their inward humilitie, Chriſtian reſolution,
<pb facs="tcp:152063:40"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:41"/>
and due acknowledgement that the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the true and eternal Sonne of God, is the onely Sauiour of the world, in whom alone all the Mercies, Graces, and Promiſes of God to mankinde for this life and the life to come are fully and wholly compriſed. None, either man, woman, or childe, of what calling ſoeuer, ſhall be otherwiſe at ſuch times buſied in the Church, then in quiet attendance to heare, marke, and vnderſtand that which is read, preached, or miniſtred; Saying in their due places audibly with the Miniſter, the Confeſsion, the Lords Prayer, and the Creed, and making ſuch other anſweres to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Prayers as are appointed in the Booke of Common prayer: neither ſhall they diſturbe the Seruice or Sermon by walking or Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, or any other way, nor depart out of the Church during the time of Seruice, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, without ſome vrgent or reaſonable cauſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XIX.</hi> Loyterers not to bee ſuffered neere the Church in time of Diuine Seruice.</head>
                  <p>THe Churchwardens or Queſtmen, and their aſsiſtants, ſhall not ſuffer any idle
<pb facs="tcp:152063:42"/>
perſons to abide either in the Churchyard or Church porch, during the time of Diuine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice or preaching: but ſhall cauſe them either to come in, or to depart.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XX.</hi> Bread and Wine to be prouided againſt euery Communion.</head>
                  <p>THe Churchwardens of euery Pariſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the time of euery Communion, ſhal at the charge of the Pariſh, with the aduice and direction of the Miniſter, prouide a ſufficient quantitie of fine white Bread, and of good and wholeſome Wine for the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Communicants that ſhall from time to time receiue there: which Wine we require to bee brought to the Communion Table in a cleane and ſweete ſtanding Pot, or Stoope of Pewter, if not of purer mettall.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XXI.</hi> The Communion to be thrice a yeere receiued.</head>
                  <p>IN euery Pariſh Church and Chappel where Sacraments are to bee adminiſtred within this Realme, the holy Communion ſhall bee miniſtred by the Parſon, Vicar, or Miniſter, ſo often, and at ſuch times as euery Pariſhioner
<pb facs="tcp:152063:42"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:43"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
may Communicate at the leaſt thriſe in the yeere (whereof the Feaſt of Eaſter to bee one) according as they are appointed by the booke of Common Prayer. Prouided, that euery Miniſter as oft as hee adminiſtreth the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, ſhall firſt receiue the Sacrament him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Furthermore no Bread or Wine newly brought ſhalbe vſed: but firſt the words of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution ſhalbe rehearſed when the ſaid Bread and Wine bee preſent vpon the Communion Table. Likewiſe the Miniſter ſhal deliuer both the Bread and the Wine to euery Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant ſeuerally.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XXII.</hi> Warning to be giuen beforehand for the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</head>
                  <p>WHereas euery Lay perſon is bound to receiue the holy Communion thrice euery yeere, and many not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding doe not receiue that Sacrament once in a yeere: We doe require euery Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to giue warning to his Pariſhioners pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely in the Church at Morning prayer the Sunday before euery time of his adminiſtring
<pb facs="tcp:152063:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that holy Sacrament, for their better prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of themſelues: Which ſaid warning, We enioyne the ſayd Pariſhioners to accept and obey vnder the penaltie and danger of the Law.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XXIII.</hi> Students in Colledges to receiue the Communion foure times a yeere.</head>
                  <p>IN all Colledges and Halles within both the Vniuerſities, the Maſters and Fellowes, ſuch eſpecially as haue any Pupils, ſhall be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that all their ſaid Pupils, and the reſt that remaine amongſt them be wel brought vp and throughly inſtructed in poynts of Religion, &amp; that they doe diligently frequent publike Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and Sermons, and receiue the holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion: which we ordaine to be adminiſtred in all ſuch Colledges and Halles the firſt or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Sunday of euery Moneth, Requiring all the ſayd Maſters, Fellowes, and Schollers, and all the reſt of the Students, Officers and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſeruants there ſo to be ordered, that euery one of them ſhall Communicate foure times in the yeere at the leaſt, kneeling reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently and decently vpon their knees accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:152063:44"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:45"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:45"/>
to the order of the Communion Booke preſcribed in that behalfe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XXIIII.</hi> Copes to be worne in Cathedral Churches by thoſe that adminiſter the Communion.</head>
                  <p>IN all Cathedrall and Collegiat Churches, the holy Communion ſhall bee adminiſtred vpon principall Feaſt-dayes, ſometimes by the Biſhop if he be preſent, and ſometimes by the Deane: and at ſome times by a Canon or Prebendarie, the principall Miniſter vſing a decent Coape, and being aſsiſted with the Goſpeller and Epiſtler agreeably according to the Aduertiſements publiſhed <hi>Anno</hi> 7. <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bethae</hi>: the ſaid Communion to bee admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred at ſuch times and with ſuch limitation, as is ſpecified in the Booke of Common prayer. Prouided, that no ſuch limitation by any conſtruction ſhall bee allowed of, but that all Deanes, Wardens, Maſters, or Heads of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall and Collegiate Churches, Prebenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Canons, Vicars, Petticannons, Singing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and all others of the Foundation, ſhall receiue the Communion foure times yeerely at the leaſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:46"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>XXV.</hi> Surpliſses and Hoods to bee worne in Cathedrall Churches when there is no Communion.</head>
                  <p>IN the time of Diuine Seruice and Prayers in all Cathedrall and Collegiat Churches, when there is no Communion, it ſhall bee ſufficient to weare Surpliſſes: ſauing that all Deanes, Maſters and Heads of Collegiat Churches, Canons and Prebendaries being Graduats, ſhal daily at the times both of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Preaching, weare with their Surpliſſes, ſuch Hoods as are agreeable to their degrees.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XXVI.</hi> Notorious offendours not to bee admitted to the Communion.</head>
                  <p>NO Miniſter ſhal in any wiſe admit to the receiuing of the holy Communion, any of his Cure or Flocke which bee openly knowen to liue in ſinne notorious without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, Nor any who haue maliciouſly and openly contended with their neighbours, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they ſhall be reconciled: Nor any Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens or Sidemen, who hauing taken their oathes to preſent to their Ordinaries all ſuch publike offences as they are particularly char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb facs="tcp:152063:46"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:47"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to inquire of in their ſeuerall Pariſhes ſhall (notwithſtanding their ſaid oathes, and that their faithfull diſcharging of them, is the chiefe meanes whereby publike ſinnes and offences may be reformed and puniſhed) wittingly and willingly, deſperately and irreligiouſly incurre the horrible crime of Periurie, either in negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting or in refuſing to preſent ſuch of the ſayd enormities and publike offences, as they know themſelues to be committed in their ſayd Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, or are notoriouſly offenſiue to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation there: although they bee vrged by ſome of their neighbours, or by their Miniſter, or by their Ordinary himſelfe, to diſcharge their conſciences by preſenting of them, and not to incurre ſo deſperately the ſaid horrible ſinne of Periurie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XXVII.</hi> Schiſmaticks not to be admitted to the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion.</head>
                  <p>NO Miniſter when hee celebrateth the Communion, ſhall wittingly adminiſter the ſame to any, but to ſuch as kneele, vnder paine of ſuſpenſion, nor vnder the like paine to any that refuſe to bee preſent at pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Prayers, according to the Orders of the
<pb facs="tcp:152063:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Church of England, nor to any that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and notorious deprauers of the Booke of Common Prayer, and adminiſtration of the Sacraments, and of the Orders, Rites, and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies therein preſcribed, or of any thing that is conteined in any of the Articles agreed vpon in the Conuocation 1562. or of any thing conteined in the Book of ordering Prieſts and Biſhops, or to any that haue ſpoken againſt and depraued his Maieſties ſoueraigne Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall: Except euery ſuch perſon ſhall firſt acknowledge to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter before the Churchwardens, his repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for the ſame, and promiſe by word (if he cannot write) that hee will doe ſo no more: and except (if he can write) he ſhall firſt do the ſame vnder his hand-writing, to bee deliuered to the Miniſter, and by him ſent to the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, or Ordinarie of the place. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided that euery Miniſter ſo repelling any (as is ſpecified either in this or in the next prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Conſtitution) ſhall vpon complaint, or being required by the Ordinarie, ſignifie the cauſe thereof vnto him, and therein obey his Order and direction.
<pb facs="tcp:152063:48"/>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:49"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:49"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>XXVIII.</hi> Strangers not to be admitted to the Communion.</head>
                  <p>THe Churchwardens or Queſtmen, and their Aſsiſtants, ſhall marke aſwell as the Miniſter, whether all and euery of the Pariſhioners, come ſo often euery yeere to the holy Communion as the Lawes and our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions do require: And whether any Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers come often and commonly from other Pariſhes to their Church, and ſhall ſhew their Miniſter of them, leſt perhaps they be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Lords Table amongſt others: which they ſhall forbid, and remit ſuch home to their owne pariſh Churches and Miniſters, there to receiue the Communion with the reſt of their owne neighbours.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XXIX.</hi> Fathers not to be Godfathers in Baptiſme, nor children not Communicants.</head>
                  <p>NO Parent ſhall bee vrged to bee preſent, nor bee admitted to anſwere as Godfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for his owne child: nor any Godfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or Godmother ſhalbe ſuffred to make any other anſwere or ſpeech, then by the Booke of Common prayer is preſcribed in that behalfe.
<pb facs="tcp:152063:50"/>
Neither ſhall any perſon be admitted Godfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or Godmother to any child at Chriſtning or Confirmation, before the ſaid perſon ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking hath receiued the holy Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XXX.</hi> The lawfull vſe of the Croſse in Baptiſme expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</head>
                  <p>WEe are ſorie that his Maieſties moſt princely care and paines taken in the Conference at Hampton Court, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many other points, touching this one of the Croſſe in Baptiſme, hath taken no better effect with many, but that ſtill the vſe of it in Baptiſme is ſo greatly ſtuck at and impugned. For the further declaration therfore of the true vſe of this Ceremonie, and for the remouing of all ſuch ſcruple as might any wayes trouble the conſciences of them who are indeed right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly religious, following the royall ſteps of our moſt worthy King, becauſe he therein follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the rules of the Scriptures, and the practiſe of the Primitiue Church: we do commend to al the true members of the Church of England theſe our directions &amp; obſeruations enſuing.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, it is to be obſerued, that although the
<pb facs="tcp:152063:50"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:51"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Iewes &amp; Ethnicks derided both the Apoſtles, and the reſt of the Chriſtians for preaching and beleeuing in him who was crucified vpon the Croſſe: yet all both Apoſtles and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were ſo farre from beeing diſcouraged from their profeſsion by the ignominie of the Croſſe, as they rather reioyced and triumphed in it. Yea, the holy Ghoſt by the mouthes of the Apoſtles did honour the Name of the Croſſe (being hatefull among the Iewes) ſo farre, that vnder it, he comprehended not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Chriſt crucified, but the force, effects, and merits of his Death and Paſsion, with all the comforts, fruits, and promiſes which wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue or expect thereby.</p>
                  <p>Secondlly, the honour and dignitie of the Name of the Croſſe, begat a reuerend eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion euen in the Apoſtles times (for ought that is knowen to the contrary) of the ſigne of the Croſſe: which the Chriſtians ſhortly after v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in all their actions, thereby making an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhew &amp; profeſsion euen to the aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Iewes, that they were not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to acknowledge him for their Lord and Sauiour, who died for them vpon the Croſſe.
<pb facs="tcp:152063:52"/>
And this ſigne they did not onely vſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with a kinde of glory, when they met with any Iewes, but ſigned therewith their children when they were Chriſtned, to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate them by that badge to his ſeruice, whoſe benefits beſtowed vpon them in Baptiſme, the name of the Croſſe did repreſent. And this vſe of the ſigne of the Croſſe in Baptiſme was held in the Primitiue Church, as well by the Greekes as the Latines, with one conſent and great applauſe. At what time, if any had oppoſed themſelues againſt it, they would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely haue beene cenſured as enemies of the name of the Croſſe, &amp; conſequently of Chriſts merits, the ſigne whereof they could no better endure. This continuall and generall vſe of the ſigne of the Croſſe, is euident by many te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of the ancient Fathers.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, it muſt be confeſſed that in proceſſe of time, the ſigne of the Croſſe was greatly ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed in the Church of Rome, eſpecially after that corruption of Popery had once poſſeſſed it But the abuſe of a thing doth not take away the lawfull vſe of it. Nay, ſo farre was it from the purpoſe of the Church of England, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake
<pb facs="tcp:152063:52"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:53"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:53"/>
and reiect the Churches of Italie, France, Spaine, Germany, or any ſuch like Churches in all things which they helde and practiſed, that, as the Apologie of the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land confeſſeth, it doth with reuerence retaine thoſe Ceremonies which doe neither endam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage the Church of God, nor offende the minds of ſober men: and onely departed from them in thoſe particular points, wherein they were fallen both from themſelues in their anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent integritie, &amp; from the Apoſtolicall Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches which were their firſt founders. In which reſpect, amongſt ſome other very ancient Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, the ſigne of the Croſſe in Baptiſme hath bene retained in this Church both by the iudgement and practiſe of thoſe reuerend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and great Diuines in the dayes of King Edward the ſixth, of whom ſome conſtantly ſuffered for the profeſsion of the trueth: and others being exiled in the time of Queene Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, did after their returne in the beginning of the Reigne of our late dread Soueraigne, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually defend and vſe the ſame. This reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution and practiſe of our Church hath beene allowed and approoued by the cenſure vpon
<pb facs="tcp:152063:54"/>
the Communion Booke in King Edward the ſixt his dayes, and by the harmonie of confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of latter yeeres: becauſe in deede the vſe of this ſigne in Baptiſme was euer accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied here with ſuch ſufficient cautions and exceptions againſt all Popiſh Superſtition and errour, as in the like caſes are either fit or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, the Church of England ſince the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of Poperie hath euer held and taught, and ſo doth hold and teach ſtill, that the ſigne of the Croſſe vſed in Baptiſme, is no part of the ſubſtance of that Sacrament. For when the Miniſter dipping the Infant in Water, or lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Water vpon the face of it (as the maner alſo is) hath pronounced theſe wordes, <hi>I bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize thee in the Name of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the holy Ghost,</hi> the Infant is fully and perfectly baptized. So as the ſigne of the Croſſe being afterwards vſed, doeth neither adde any thing to the vertue or perfection of Baptiſme, nor being omitted doeth detract a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing from the effect and ſubſtance of it.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, it is apparant in the Communion Booke, that the Infant baptized is by vertue of
<pb facs="tcp:152063:54"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:55"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:55"/>
Baptiſme, before it be ſigned with the ſigne of the Croſſe, receiued into the Congregation of Chriſts flocke as a perfect member thereof, and not by any power aſcribed vnto the ſigne of the Croſſe So that for the very remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the Croſſe, which is very precious to all them that rightly beleeue in <hi>Ieſu Chriſt,</hi> and in the other reſpects mentioned, the Church of England hath reteined ſtill the ſigne of it in Baptiſme: following therein the Primitiue and Apoſtolicall Churches, &amp; accounting it a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful outward Ceremony &amp; honourable Badge, whereby the Infant is dedicated to the ſeruice of him that died vpon the Croſſe, as by the words vſed in the Booke of Common prayer it may appeare.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, the vſe of the ſigne of the Croſſe in Baptiſme, beeing thus purged from all Popiſh ſuperſtition and errour, and reduced in the Church of England to the primary Inſtitution of it vpon thoſe true rules of Doctrine concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning things indifferent, which are conſonant to the word of God, and the iudgements of all the ancient Fathers: Wee hold it the part of euery priuate man, both Miniſter and other,
<pb facs="tcp:152063:56"/>
reuerently to reteine the true vſe of it preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by publike Authoritie, conſidering that things of themſelues indifferent, doe in ſome ſort alter their natures, when they are either commanded or forbidden by a lawfull Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate: and may not be omitted at euery mans pleaſure contrary to the Law, when they bee co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded, nor vſed when they are prohibited.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Miniſters their Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, function, and charge.</head>
               <div n="31" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XXXI.</hi> Foure ſolemne times appointed for the making of Miniſters.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as the ancient Fathers of the Church led by example of the Apoſtles, appointed Prayers and Faſts to bee vſed at the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne ordering of Miniſters, &amp; to that purpoſe allotted certaine times, in which onely ſacred Orders might be giuen or conferred: We fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing their holy and Religious example, doe conſtitute &amp; decree, That no Deacons or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters be made and ordained, but onely vpon
<pb facs="tcp:152063:56"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:57"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the Sundayes immediatly following <hi>Ieiunia quatuor temporum,</hi> commonly called Ember weekes, appointed in ancient time for Prayer and Faſting (purpoſely for this cauſe at their firſt Inſtitution) and ſo continued at this day in the Church of England: and that this bee done in the Cathedrall or Pariſh Church where the Biſhop reſideth, and in the time of diuine Seruice, in the preſence not onely of the Archdeacon, but of the Deane and two Prebendaries at the leaſt, or (if they ſhall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen by any lawful cauſe to be let or hindered) in the preſence of foure other graue perſons being maſters of Arts at the leaſt, and allowed for publike Preachers.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="32" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XXXII.</hi> None to bee made Deacon and Miniſter, both in one day.</head>
                  <p>THe Office of a Deacon being a ſtep or degree to the Miniſtery according to the iudgment of the ancient Fathers, and the practiſe of the Primitiue Church: We doe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine and appoint, that hereafter no Biſhop ſhall make any perſon of what qualities or gifts ſoeuer, a Deacon and a Miniſter, both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb facs="tcp:152063:58"/>
vpon one day: but that the order in that behalfe preſcribed in the Booke of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and conſecrating Biſhops, Prieſtes, and Deacons be ſtrictly obſerued. Not that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes euery Deacon ſhould be kept from the Miniſterie for a whole yeere when the Biſhop ſhall find good cauſe to the contrary: but that there being now foure times appointed in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry yeere for the ordination of Deacons and Miniſters, there may euer be ſome time of trial of their behauiour in the office of Deacon, before they bee admitted to the Order of Prieſthood.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XXXIII.</hi> The Titles of ſuch as are to be made Miniſters.</head>
                  <p>IT hath beene long ſince prouided by many decrees of the ancient Fathers, that none ſhould be admitted either Deacon or Prieſt, who had not firſt ſome certain place where he might vſe his Function. According to which examples we doe ordaine, that henceforth no perſon ſhall be admitted into ſacred Orders, except he ſhall at that time exhibite to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of whome hee deſireth Impoſition of hands, a preſentation of himſelfe to ſome Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall
<pb facs="tcp:152063:58"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:59"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:59"/>
preferment then voyd in that Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe: or ſhal bring to the ſaid Biſhop a true &amp; vndoubted Certificate, that either he is proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of ſome Church within the ſaid Dioceſſe, where he may attend the Cure of ſoules, or of ſome Miniſters place vacant, either in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral Church of that Dioceſſe, or in ſome other Collegiat Church therein alſo ſcituate, where he may execute his Miniſterie: or that he is a Fellow, or in right as a Fellow, or to bee a Conduct or Chapleine in ſome Colledge in Cambridge or Oxford: or except he be a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Arts of fiue yeeres ſtanding, that liueth of his owne charge in either of the Vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: or except by the Biſhop himſelfe, that doth ordaine him Miniſter, he be ſhortly after to be admitted either to ſome Benefice or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateſhip then voyd. And if any Biſhop ſhall admit any perſon into the Miniſtery that hath none of theſe Titles as is aforeſaid, then he ſhal keepe and maintaine him with all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, till he doe preferre him to ſome Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical liuing. And if the ſaid Biſhop ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe ſo to doe, hee ſhall bee ſuſpended by the Archbiſhop being aſsiſted with another Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop,
<pb facs="tcp:152063:60"/>
from giuing of Orders by the ſpace of a yeere.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="34" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XXXIIII.</hi> The qualitie of ſuch as are to bee made Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters.</head>
                  <p>NO Biſhop ſhall hencefoorth admit any perſon into ſacred Orders which is not of his owne Dioceſſe, except he be either of one of the Vniuerſities of this Realme, or except hee ſhall bring letters Dimiſſory (ſo tearmed) from the Biſhop of whoſe Dioceſſe he is, and deſiring to be a Deacon, is three and twentie yeeres olde, and to bee a Prieſt foure and twenty yeeres complete, and hath taken ſome degree of Schoole in either of the ſaide Vniuerſities, or at the leaſt, except hee be able to yeeld an accompt of his Faith in Latine, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Articles of Religion approoued in the Synode of the Biſhops and Cleargie of this Realme 1562, and to confirme the ſame by ſufficient teſtimonies out of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and except moreouer, he ſhall then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibite letters Teſtimoniall of his good life and conuerſation vnder the Seale of ſome College in Cambridge or Oxford, where before he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained,
<pb facs="tcp:152063:60"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:61"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:61"/>
or of three or foure graue Miniſters, together with the ſubſcription and teſtimonie of other credible perſons, who haue knowen his life and behauiour by the ſpace of three yeeres next before.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="35" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XXXV.</hi> The examination of ſuch as are to bee made Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters.</head>
                  <p>THe Biſhop before hee admit any perſon to holy Orders, ſhall diligently examine him in the preſence of thoſe Miniſters that ſhal aſsiſt him at the Impoſition of hands. And if the ſaid Biſhop haue any lawfull impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment, he ſhall cauſe the ſaid Miniſters care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to examine euery ſuch perſon ſo to bee ordered. Prouided that they who ſhall aſsiſt the Biſhop in examining and laying on of handes, ſhall bee of his Cathedrall Church if they may conueniently bee had, or other ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Preachers of the ſame Dioceſſe, to the number of three at the leaſt. And if any biſhop or Suffragan ſhal admit any to ſacred Orders who is not ſo qualified &amp; examined, as before we haue ordeined: the Archbiſhop of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince hauing notice thereof, &amp; being aſsiſted
<pb facs="tcp:152063:62"/>
therein by one Biſhop, ſhall ſuſpend the ſaid Biſhop or Suffragan ſo offending, from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king either Deacons or Prieſts for the ſpace of two yeeres.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="36" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XXXVI.</hi> Subſcription required of ſuch as are to bee made Ministers.</head>
                  <p>NO perſon ſhall hereafter be receiued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Miniſtery, nor either by Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Collation admitted to any Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical liuing, nor ſuffered to Preach, to Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chize, or to be a Lecturer, or Reader of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie in either Vniuerſity, or in any Cathedrall or Collegiat Church, City or market Towne, pariſh Church, Chappel, or in any other place within this Realme, except hee be licenſed ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Archbiſhop, or by the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, (where he is to be placed) vnder their handes and ſeales, or by one of the two Vniuerſities vnder their ſeale likewiſe: and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he ſhall firſt ſubſcribe to theſe three Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles following, in ſuch maner and ſort as wee haue here appointed.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 That the Kings Maieſtie vnder God, is the onely ſupreme Gouernour of this Realme,
<pb facs="tcp:152063:62"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:63"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:63"/>
and of all other his Highneſſe Dominions and Countreys, aſwell in all Spirituall or Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall things or cauſes, as Temporall and that no forraine Prince, perſon, prelate, State, or potentate, hath or ought to haue any Iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, power, ſuperioritie, preheminence, or authoritie Eccleſiaſticall or Spirituall, within his Maieſties ſaid Realmes, Dominions, and Countreys.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 That the Booke of Common prayer, and of ordering of Biſhops, prieſts and dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, containeth in it nothing contrary to the word of God, and that it may lawfully ſo be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and that he himſelfe will vſe the forme in the ſaid Booke preſcribed in publike prayer, and adminiſtration of the Sacraments, and none other.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 That he alloweth the booke of Articles of Religion agreed vpon oy the Archbiſhops and Biſhops of both Prouinces, and the whole Cleargie in the Conuocation holden at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don in the yeere of our Lord God, one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand fiue hundred ſixtie and two: and that he acknowledgeth all &amp; euery the Articles there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contained being in number nine and thirty,
<pb facs="tcp:152063:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>
beſides the ratification, to be agreeable to the word of God.</p>
                  <p>To theſe three Articles whoſoeuer will ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, he ſhal for the auoyding of all ambigui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſubſcribe in this order &amp; fourme of words, ſetting downe both his chriſten and ſurname, <hi>viz. I N. N. doe willingly and</hi> ex animo <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to theſe three Articles aboue mentioned, and to all things that are contained in them.</hi> And if any biſhop ſhall ordaine, admit, or licenſe any as is aforeſaid, except hee firſt haue ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in maner and fourme as here we haue appointed, he ſhall be ſuſpended from giuing of Orders and Licences to preach for the ſpace of twelue moneths. But if either of the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities ſhall offend therein, wee leaue them to the danger of the Lawe and his Maieſties cenſure.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="37" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XXXVII.</hi> Subſcription before the Dioceſan.</head>
                  <p>NOne licenſed as is aforeſaid, to Preach, Reade, Lecture, or Catechize, comming to reſide in any Dioceſſe, ſhalbe permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted there to Preach, Read, Lecture, Catechize, or Miniſter the Sacraments, or to execute any
<pb facs="tcp:152063:64"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:65"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>
other Eccleſiaſticall function (by what autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie ſoeuer he be thereunto admitted) vnleſſe he firſt conſent and ſubſcribe to the three Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles before mentioned, in the preſence of the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe wherin he is to preach, Read, Lecture, Cathechize or adminiſter the Sacraments as aforeſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="38" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XXXVIII.</hi> Reuolters after Subſcription, cenſured.</head>
                  <p>IF any Miniſter after he hath once ſubſcribed to the ſaid three Articles, ſhal omit to vſe the fourme of Prayer, or any of the Orders or Ceremonies preſcribed in the Communion Booke, let him be ſuſpended: and if after a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth he doe not reforme and ſubmit himſelfe, let him be exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated: and then if he ſhal not ſubmit himſelf within the ſpace of another moneth, let him be depoſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Miniſtery.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="39" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XXXIX.</hi> Cautions for Inſtitution of Ministers into Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices.</head>
                  <p>NO biſhop ſhall inſtitute any to a Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, who hath bene ordained by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Biſhop, except hee firſt ſhew vnto him his Letters of Orders, and bring him a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
<pb facs="tcp:152063:66"/>
teſtimony of his former good life and behauiour, if the Biſhop ſhall require it: and laſtly ſhall appeare vpon due examination to be worthy of his Miniſtery.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="40" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XL.</hi> An Oath against Symonie at institution into Benefices.</head>
                  <p>TO auoid the deteſtable ſinne of Symony, becauſe buying &amp; ſelling of Spiritual and Eccleſiaſtical Functions, Offices, Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Dignities, and Liuings is execrable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God: therefore the Archbiſhop and all and euery Biſhop or Biſhops or any other perſon or perſons, hauing authority to Admit, Inſtitute, Collate, Inſtall, or to confirme the election of any Archbiſhop, Biſhop, or other perſon or perſons to any Spirituall or Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall function, Dignitie, Promotion, Title, Office, Iuriſdiction, Place, or Benefice with Cure or without Cure, or to any Eccleſiaſtical liuing whatſoeuer, ſhall before euery ſuch Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion, Inſtitution, Collation, Inſtallation or Confirmation of Election, reſpectiuely mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to euery perſon hereafter to be admitted, Inſtituted, collated, Inſtalled, or confirmed in
<pb facs="tcp:152063:66"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:67"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:67"/>
or to any Archbiſhopricke, Biſhopricke, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical function, Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Promotion, Title, office, Iuriſdiction, Place, or Benefice with Cure or without Cure, or in or to any Eccleſiaſticall liuing whatſoeuer, this Oath in maner and forme following, the ſame to be taken by euery one whom it concerneth in his owne perſon, and not by a Proctor: <hi>I N. N. do ſweare, That I haue made no Symoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acall payment, contract or promiſe, directly or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly, by my ſelfe or by any other to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or with my conſent, to any perſon or perſons whatſoeuer, for or concerning the procuring and obtaining of this Eccleſiaſticall Dignity, Place, Preferment, Office or Liuing,</hi> (reſpectiuely and particularly naming the ſame whereunto hee is to be Admitted, Inſtituted, Collated, Inſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, or Confirmed) <hi>nor will at any time hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter perfourme or ſatiſfie any ſuch kind of paiment, contract or promiſe made by any other without my knowledge or conſent; So helpe me God through Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="41" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XLI.</hi> Licenſes for plurality of Benefices limitted, and Reſidence enioyned.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:68"/>NO Licenſe or diſpenſation for the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of more Benefices with Cure then one, ſhalbe granted to any, but ſuch on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as ſhall be thought very well worthy for his learning, and very well able and ſufficient to diſcharge his duety, that is, who ſhall haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the degree of a Maſter of Arts at the leaſt in one of the Vniuerſities of this Realme, and bee a publike and ſufficient Preacher licenſed. Prouided alwayes that he bee by a good and ſufficient caution bound to make his perſonall Reſidence in each his ſayd Benefices for ſome reaſonable time in euery yeere: and that the ſayd Benefices bee not more then thirty miles diſtant ſunder: and laſtly, that he haue vnder him in the Benefice where he doeth not reſide, a Preacher lawfully allowed, that is able ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently to teach and inſtruct the people.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="42" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XLII.</hi> Reſidence of Deanes in their Churches.</head>
                  <p>EVery Deane, Maſter, or Warden, or chiefe Gouernour of any Cathedrall or Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giate Church, ſhall be reſident in his ſaid Cathedrall or Collegiate Church foureſcore and ten dayes <hi>Coniunctim</hi> or <hi>Diuiſim</hi> in euery
<pb facs="tcp:152063:68"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:69"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:69"/>
yeere at the leaſt, and then ſhal continue there in preaching the word of God, and keeping good hoſpitalitie, except he ſhall be otherwiſe let with weighty and vrgent cauſes to bee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued by the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, or in any other lawfull ſort diſpenſed with. And when he is preſent, he, with the reſt of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons or Prebendaries reſident, ſhall take ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all care, that the Statutes and laudable Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes of their Church, (not being contrary to the word of God, or Prerogatiue Royall) the Statutes of this Realme being in force con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Eccleſiaſticall Order, and all other Conſtitutions now ſet foorth and confirmed by his Maieſties Authoritie, and ſuch as ſhall bee lawfully enioyned by the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe in his Viſitation according to the Statutes and Cuſtomes of the ſame Church, or the Eccleſiaſticall Lawes of this Realme, be diligently obſerued, and that the Pettie Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, Vicars chorall, and other Miniſters of their Church be vrged to the ſtudy of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures: and euery one of them to haue the New Teſtament not onely in Engliſh, but alſo in Latine.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="43" type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:70"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>XLIII.</hi> Deanes and Prebendaries to Preach during their Reſidence.</head>
                  <p>THe Deane, Maſter, Warden, or chiefe Gouernour, Prebendaries and Canons in euery Cathedral &amp; Collegiat Church, ſhal not onely preach there in their owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo often as they are bound by Law, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, Ordinance, or Cuſtome; but ſhall like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Preach in other Churches of the ſame Dioceſſe where they are reſident, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in thoſe places whence they or their Church receiue any yeerely Rents or profits. And in caſe they themſelues bee ſicke, or law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully abſent, they ſhall ſubſtitute ſuch licenſed Preachers to ſupplie their turnes, as by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of the Dioceſſe ſhal be thought meete to Preach in Cathedrall Churches. And if any otherwiſe neglect to omit or ſupply his courſe, as is aforeſaid, the offendor ſhall be puniſhed by the Biſhop, or by him or them to whome the iuriſdiction of that Church appertaineth, according to the quality of the offence.
<pb facs="tcp:152063:70"/>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="44" type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:71"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:71"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>XLIIII.</hi> Prebendaries to be reſident vpon their Benefices.</head>
                  <p>NO Prebendaries nor Canons in Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall or Collegiate Churches, hauing one or moe Benefices with Cure, (and not beeing Reſidentaries in the ſame Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall or Collegiat Churches) ſhall vnder co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of the ſayd Prebends, abſent themſelues from their Benefices with Cure aboue the ſpace of one moneth in the yeere, vnleſſe it be for ſome vrgent cauſe, and certaine time to be allowed by the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe. And ſuch of the ſaid Canons and Prebendaries as by the Ordinances of the ſayd Cathedrall or Collegiat Churches do ſtand bound to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident in the ſame, ſhall ſo among themſelues ſort and proportion the times of the yeere, concerning reſidence to bee kept in the ſayde Churches, as that ſome of them alwayes ſhall be perſonally reſident there: and that all thoſe who be, or ſhall be Reſidentiaries in any Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall or Collegiat Church, ſhall after the dayes of their Reſidencie appointed by their locall Statutes or Cuſtomes expired, preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repaire to their Benefices, or ſome one of
<pb facs="tcp:152063:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>
them, or to ſome other Charge where the Law requireth their preſence, there to diſcharge their dueties according to the Lawes in that caſe prouided. And the Biſhop of the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe ſhall ſee the ſame to be duely performed and put in execution.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="45" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XLV.</hi> Beneficed Preachers beeing reſident vpon their liuings to preach euery Sunday.</head>
                  <p>EVery Beneficed man allowed to bee a preacher, and reſiding on his Benefice, hauing no lawful impediment, ſhall in his owne Cure, or in ſome other Church or Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell where he may conueniently neere adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, (where no Preacher is) preach one Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon euery Sunday of the yeere, wherein hee ſhall ſoberly and ſincerely diuide the word of trueth to the glory of God, and to the beſt edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the people.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="46" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XLVI.</hi> Beneficed men not Preachers to procure moneth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sermons.</head>
                  <p>EVery beneficed man not allowed to be a Preacher, ſhall procure Sermons to bee preached in his Cure once in euery mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb facs="tcp:152063:72"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:73"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:73"/>
at the leaſt, by Preachers lawfully licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, if his liuing in the iudgement of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, will be able to beare it. And vpon euery Sunday when there ſhall not bee a Sermon preached in his Cure, hee or his Curate ſhall reade ſome one of the Homilies preſcribed, or to be preſcribed by authoritie to the intents a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="47" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XLVII.</hi> Abſence of Beneficed men to bee ſupplied by Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates that are allowed Preachers.</head>
                  <p>EVery Beneficed man licenſed by the Lawes of this Realme, vpon vrgent occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of other ſeruice not to reſide vpon his Benefice, ſhall cauſe his Cure to be ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a Curate that is a ſuffiicient and licenſed Preacher, if the worth of the Benefice wil beare it. But whoſoeuer hath two Benefices, ſhall maintaine a Preacher licenſed, in the Benefice where he doeth not reſide, except he preach himſelfe at both of them vſually.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="48" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XLVIII.</hi> None to be Curates but allowed by the Biſhop.</head>
                  <p>NO Curat or Miniſter ſhall be permited to ſerue in any place, without Examination
<pb facs="tcp:152063:74"/>
and Admiſsion of the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe or Ordinary of the place hauing Epiſcopal Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, in writing vnder his hand and ſeale, hauing reſpect to the greatneſſe of the Cure, and meeteneſſe of the party. And the ſaid Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates and Miniſters if they remooue from one Dioceſſe to another, ſhal not be by any means admitted to ſerue without teſtimonie of the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, or Ordinarie of the place as aforeſaid, whence they came, in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, of their honeſty, ability, and conformitie to the Eccleſiaſticall lawes of the Church of England. Nor any ſhall ſerue more then one Church or Chappel vpon one day, except that Chappell be a member of the Pariſh Church, or vnited thereunto: and vnleſſe the ſayde Church or Chappell where ſuch a Miniſter ſhall ſerue in two places, bee not able in the iudgement of the Biſhop or Ordinary as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid to maintaine a Curate.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="49" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XLIX.</hi> Miniſters not allowed Preachers, may not expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</head>
                  <p>NO perſon whatſoeuer not examined and approued by the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, or not licenſed as is aforeſaid for a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
<pb facs="tcp:152063:74"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:75"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>
or conuenient Preacher, ſhal take vpon him to expound in his owne Cure or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, any Scripture or matter of doctrine, but ſhall onely ſtudy to reade plainly and apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (without glozing or adding) the <hi>Homilies</hi> already ſet foorth or hereafter to be publiſhed by lawfull Authoritie, for the confirmation of the true Faith, and for the good inſtruction and edification of the people.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="50" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>L.</hi> Strangers not admitted to Preach without ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Licence.</head>
                  <p>NEither the Miniſter, Churchwardens, nor any other Officers of the Church, ſhall ſuffer any man to preach within their Churches or Chappels, but ſuch as by ſhewing their Licence to preach, ſhal appeare vnto them to be ſufficiently authorized there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, as is aforeſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="51" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LI.</hi> Strangers not admitted to Preach in Cathedrall Churches without ſufficient authoritie.</head>
                  <p>THe Dea<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>, Preſidents, &amp; Reſidentiaries of any Cathedrall or Collegiate Church, ſhal ſuffer no ſtranger to preach vnto the
<pb facs="tcp:152063:76"/>
people in their Churches, except they be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Archbiſhop of the Prouince, or by the Biſhop of the ſame Dioceſſe, or by ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Vniuerſities. And if any in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſhal publiſh any Doctrine, either ſtrange or diſagreeing from the word of God, or from any of the Articles of Religion agreed vpon in the Conuocation houſe <hi>Anno</hi> 1562. or from the booke of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon prayers: the Deane or the Reſidents ſhall by their Letters ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed with ſome of their hands that heard him, ſo ſoone as may be, giue notice of the ſame to the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, that he may deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the matter, and take ſuch order therein as he ſhall thinke conuenient.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="52" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LII.</hi> The names of ſtrange Preachers to bee noted in a Booke.</head>
                  <p>THat the Biſhop may vnderſtand (if oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ſo require) what Sermons are made in euery Church of his Dioceſſe, and who preſume to preach without Licence: the Churchwardens &amp; Sidemen ſhall ſee that the names of al preachers which come to their Church from any other place, bee noted in a
<pb facs="tcp:152063:76"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:77"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:77"/>
booke, which they ſhall haue ready for that purpoſe: wherein euery Preacher ſhall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe his name, the day when hee preached, and the name of the Biſhop of whom he had Licence to preach.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="53" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LIII.</hi> No publike oppoſition betweene Preachers.</head>
                  <p>IF any Preacher ſhall in the Pulpit particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, or namely of purpoſe, impugne or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute any doctrine deliuered by any other Preacher in the ſame Church, or in any church neere adioyning, before he hath acquainted the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe therewith, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued order from him what to do in that caſe, becauſe vpon ſuch publike diſſenting and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting, there may grow much offence and diſquietneſſe vnto the people: the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens or party grieued ſhall forthwith ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the ſame to the ſaid Biſhop, and not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the ſaid Preacher any more to occupy that place which he hath once abuſed, except hee faithfully promiſe to forbeare all ſuch matter of contention in the Church, vntill the Biſhop hath taken further order therein: who ſhall with all conuenient ſpeed ſo proceed therein,
<pb facs="tcp:152063:78"/>
that publike ſatisfaction may bee made in the Congregation where the offence was giuen. Prouided, that if either of the parties offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding doe appeale, hee ſhall not be ſuffered to preach <hi>pendente lite.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="54" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LIIII.</hi> The Licences of Preachers refuſing Conformitie, to be voyd.</head>
                  <p>IF any man licenced heretofore to preach, by any Archbiſhop, Biſhop, or by either of the Vniuerſities, ſhall at any time from henceforth refuſe to conforme himſelfe to the Lawes, Ordinances, and Rites Eccleſiaſticall eſtabliſhed in the Church of England, he ſhall be admoniſhed by the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, or Ordinary of the place, to ſubmit himſelfe to the vſe and due exerciſe of the ſame. And if after ſuch admonition, he doe not conforme himſelfe within the ſpace of one moneth, We determine and decree, That the licence of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuch Preacher ſhall thereupon bee vtterly voyde and of none effect.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="55" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LV.</hi> The forme of a Prayer to bee vſed by Preachers before their Sermons.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:78"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:79"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:79"/>BEfore all Sermons, Lectures, and Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, the Preachers &amp; Miniſters ſhall moue the people to ioine with them in prayer in this forme, or to this effect, as briefly as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniently they may. Ye ſhal pray for Chriſts holy Catholike Church, that is, for the whole Congregation of Chriſtian people diſperſed throughout the whole world, and eſpecially for the Churches of England, Scotland, and Ireland. And herein I require you moſt eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to pray for the Kings moſt excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, our Soueraigne Lord IAMES, King of England, Scotland, France and Ireland, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendour of the Faith, &amp; Supreme Gouernour in theſe his Realmes, and all other his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and Countries, ouer all perſons, in all cauſes, aſwell Eccleſiaſticall as Temporall. Ye ſhall alſo pray for our gracious Queene ANNE, the Noble Prince HENRY, and the reſt of the King and Queenes Royall Iſſue. Ye ſhall alſo pray for the Miniſters of Gods holy word &amp; Sacraments, aſwell Archbiſhops and Biſhops, as other Paſtours and Curates. Ye ſhall alſo pray for the Kings moſt honourable Counſell, and for all the Nobilitie and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates
<pb facs="tcp:152063:80"/>
of this Realme, that all &amp; euery of theſe in their ſeuerall Callings, may ſerue truely and painefully to the glory of God, and the edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and well gouerning of his people, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring the accompt that they muſt make. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo yee ſhall pray for the whole Commons of this Realme, that they may liue in true Faith and feare of God, in humble obedience to the King, and brotherly charitie one to another. Finally, let vs praiſe God for all thoſe which are departed out of this life in the Faith of Chriſt, and pray vnto God that wee may haue grace to direct our liues after their good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: that this life ended, wee may be made partakers with them of the glorious Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the life Euerlaſting, alwayes conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with the Lords prayer.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="56" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LVI.</hi> Preachers and Lecturers to reade diuine Seruice and adminiſter the Sacraments twiſe a yeere at the leaſt.</head>
                  <p>EVery Miniſter being poſſeſſed of a Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice that hath Cure and Charge of ſoules, although he chiefly attend to preaching, and hath a Curate vnder him to execute the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:152063:80"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:81"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:81" rendition="simple:additions"/>
duties, which are to be performed for him in the Church, and likewiſe euery other ſtipen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darie Preacher that readeth any Lecture, or Catechizeth, or Preacheth in any Church or Chappell, ſhall twiſe at the leaſt euery yeere reade himſelfe the diuine Seruice, vpon two ſeuerall Sundayes, publikely and at the vſuall times, both in the Forenoone and Afternoone in the Church which he ſo poſſeſſeth, or where he Readeth, Catechizeth, or Preacheth as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, and ſhal likewiſe as often in euery yeere adminiſter the Sacraments of Baptiſme (if there be any to be baptized) &amp; of the Lords Supper, in ſuch maner &amp; forme, and with the obſeruation of all such Rites and Ceremonies as are preſcribed by the booke of Common prayer in that behalfe: which if hee doe not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly performe, then ſhall he that is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of a Benefice (as before) bee ſuſpended: and he thatis but aReader, Preacher, or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techizer, be remoued from his place by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of the Dioceſſe, vntil he or they ſhal ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelues to performe all the ſaid duties, in ſuch mater and <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ort as before is preſcribed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="57" type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:82"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>LVII.</hi> The Sacraments not to be refuſed at the hands of vnpreaching Miniſters.</head>
                  <p>WHereas diuers Perſons ſeduced by falſe Teachers, doe refuſe to haue their children baptized by a Miniſter that is no Preacher, and to receiue the holy Communion at his hands in the ſame reſpect, as though the vertue of thoſe Sacraments did depend vpon his ability to preach: Foraſmuch as the doctrine both of Baptiſme and of the Lords Supper is ſufficiently ſet downe in the booke of Common prayer to bee vſed at the adminiſtration of the ſaid Sacraments, as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be added vnto it that is material and neceſſary: We doe require and charge euery ſuch perſon ſeduced as aforeſayd, to reforme that their wilfulneſſe, and to ſubmit himſelfe to the order of the Church in that behalfe, both the ſaid Sacraments being equally effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual, whether they be miniſtred by a Miniſter that is no Preacher, or by one that is a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher. And if any hereafter ſhal offend herein, or leaue their owne Pariſh Churches in that reſpect, and Communicate or cauſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb facs="tcp:152063:82"/>
to be Baptized in other Pariſhes abroad, and will not bee mooued thereby to reforme that their error and vnlawfull courſe: let them be preſented to the Ordinarie of the place by the Miniſter, Churchwardens, and Sidemen or Queſtmen of the Pariſhes where they dwel, and there receiue ſuch puniſhment by Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall cenſures, as ſuch obſtinacie doth wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily deſerue: that is, Let them (perſiſting in their wilfulneſſe) be ſuſpended, and then after a moneths further obſtinacie, Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And likewiſe if any Parſon, Vicar, or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, ſhal after the publiſhing hereof, either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue to the Communion any ſuch perſons which are not of his owne Church &amp; Pariſh, or ſhall Baptize any of their children, thereby ſtrengthening them in their ſaid errours, Let him bee ſuſpended, and not releaſed thereof, vntill hee doe faithfully promiſe that hee will not afterwards offend therein.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="58" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LVIII.</hi> Miniſters reading Diuine Seruice, and Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the Sacraments, to weare Surpliſses, and Graduats therewithall Hoods.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:83"/>EVery Miniſter ſaying the publike Praiers, or miniſtring the Sacraments or other Rites of the Church, ſhall weare a decent and comely Surpliſſe with ſleeues, to be proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at the charge of the Pariſh. And if any queſtion ariſe touching the matter, decencie, or comlineſſe thereof, the ſame ſhalbe decided by the diſcretion of the Ordinary. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more ſuch Miniſters as are Graduats, ſhall weare vpon their Surpliſſes at ſuch times, ſuch Hoods as by the orders of the Vniuerſities are agreeable to their degrees, which no Miniſter ſhall weare (being no Graduat) vnder paine of ſuſpenſion. Notwithſtanding it ſhalbe law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for ſuch Miniſters as are not Graduats, to weare vpon their Surpliſſes in ſtead of Hoods, ſome decent Tippet of black, ſo it be not ſilke.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="59" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LIX.</hi> Miniſters to Catechize euery Sunday.</head>
                  <p>EVery Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, vpon eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sunday and Holy day before Euening prayer, ſhall for halfe an houre or more, examine and inſtruct the youth and ignorant perſons of his Pariſh in the ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the Articles of the Beliefe, and in the
<pb facs="tcp:152063:83"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:84"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:84"/>
Lords prayer: and ſhall diligently heare, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct, &amp; teach them the Catechiſme ſet forth in the Booke of Common prayer. And all Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Mothers, Maſters, and Miſtreſſes, ſhall cauſe their children, ſeruants, and apprentices, which haue not learned the Catechiſme, to come to the Church at the time appointed, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bediently to heare, and to bee ordered by the Miniſter, vntill they haue learned the ſame. And if any Miniſter neglect his duetie herein, let him bee ſharpely reprooued vpon the firſt complaint, and true notice thereof giuen to the Biſhop or Ordinarie of the place. If after ſubmitting himſelfe, hee ſhall wilfully offend therein againe, let him be ſuſpended. If ſo the third time, there being little hope that he will bee therein reformed, then Excommunicated, and ſo remaine vntil he will be reformed. And likewiſe if any of the ſaide Fathers, Mothers, Maſters, or Miſtreſſes, Children, Seruants, or Apprentices ſhall neglect their dueties, as the one ſort in not cauſing them to come, and the other in refuſing to learne as aforeſaid, Let them bee ſuſpended by their Ordinaries, (if they be not children) and if they ſo perſiſt by
<pb facs="tcp:152063:85"/>
the ſpace of a moneth, then let them bee Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="60" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LX.</hi> Confirmation to be performed once in three yeeres.</head>
                  <p>FOraſmuch as it hath beene a ſolemne, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, &amp; laudable Cuſtome in the Church of God, continued from the Apoſtles times, that all Biſhops ſhould lay their hands vpon children Baptized and inſtructed in the Catechiſme of Chriſtian Religion, praying o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them, and bleſsing them, which wee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly call <hi>Confirmation,</hi> and that this holy action hath beene accuſtomed in the Church in former ages, to be performed in the Biſhops Viſitation euery third yeere: We will and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point, that euery Biſhop, or his Suffragan in his accuſtomed Viſitation, do in his owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon carefully obſerue the ſaid Cuſtome. And if in that yeere by reaſon of ſome infirmitie, he be not able perſonally to Viſit, then he ſhal not omit the execution of that duetie of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation</hi> the next yeere after, as he may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniently.
<pb facs="tcp:152063:85"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:86"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:86"/>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="61" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXI.</hi> Miniſters to prepare children for Confirmation.</head>
                  <p>EVery Miniſter that hath Cure and charge of ſoules, for the better accompliſhing of the Orders preſcribed in the Booke of Common prayer concerning Confirmation, ſhall take ſuch eſpeciall care as that none may be preſented to the Biſhop for him to lay his hands vpon, but ſuch as can render an account of their Faith according to the Catechiſme in the ſaid Booke contained. And when the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop ſhall aſſigne any time for the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of that part of his duty, euery ſuch Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ſhall vſe his beſt endeuour to prepare and make able, and likewiſe to procure as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as he can to be then brought, and by the Biſhop to be confirmed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="62" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXII.</hi> Miniſters not to marrie any perſons without Bannes or Licence.</head>
                  <p>NO Miniſter vpon paine of ſuſpenſion <hi>per triennium ipſo facto,</hi> ſhall celebrate Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie betweene any perſons without a Facultie or Licence granted by ſome of the perſons in theſe our Conſtitutions expreſſed,
<pb facs="tcp:152063:87"/>
except the Bannes of Matrimonie haue bene firſt publiſhed three ſeueral Sundaies or Holy dayes in the time of diuine Seruice in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> churches and Chappels where the ſaide parties dwel, according to the booke of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer. Neither ſhall any Miniſter vpon the like paine vnder any pretence whatſoeuer, ioyne any perſons ſo licenced in Marriage at any vnſeaſonable times, but onely betweene the houres of eight and twelue in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, nor in any priuate place, but either in the ſaid Churches or Chappels where one of them dwelleth, and likewiſe in time of Diuine Seruice: nor when Bannes are thrice asked (and no Licence in that reſpect neceſſary) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Parents or Gouernours of the parties to be married, being vnder the age of twentie and one yeeres, ſhall either perſonally, or by ſufficient teſtimonie, ſignifie to him their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents giuen to the ſaid Marriage.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="63" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXIII.</hi> Miniſters of exempt Churches not to Marry with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Bannes or Licence.</head>
                  <p>EVery Miniſter who ſhal hereafter celebrate Marriage betwixt any perſons contrary to
<pb facs="tcp:152063:87"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:88"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:88"/>
our ſaid Conſtitutions, or any part of them, vnder colour of any peculiar Libertie or Priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge claimed to appertaine to certaine Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Chappels, ſhall be ſuſpended <hi>per tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ennium,</hi> by the Ordinarie of the place where the offence ſhalbe committed. And if any ſuch Miniſter ſhall afterwards remooue from the place where he hath committed that fault be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he be ſuſpended, as is aforeſaid, then ſhall the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, or Ordinarie of the place where he remaineth, vpon Certificat vnder the Hand and Seale of the other Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie from whoſe Iuriſdiction hee remooued, execute that cenſure vpon him.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="64" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXIIII.</hi> Miniſters ſolemnly to bid Holy dayes.</head>
                  <p>EVery Parſon, Vicar, or Curate ſhall in his ſeuerall charge declare to the people eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sunday at the time appointed in the Communion Booke, whether there bee any Holy dayes or Faſting dayes the weeke fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. And if any doe hereafter wittingly offend herein, and beeing once admoniſhed thereof by his Ordinary, ſhall againe omit that duetie: let him be cenſured according to
<pb facs="tcp:152063:89"/>
Law, vntill hee ſubmit himſelfe to the due per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="65" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXV.</hi> Miniſters ſolemnly to denounce Recuſants and Excommunicats.</head>
                  <p>ALl Ordinaries ſhall in their ſeuerall Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions carefully ſee &amp; giue order, that aſwell thoſe who for obſtinate refuſing to frequent diuine Seruice eſtabliſhed by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like authority within this Realme of England, as thoſe alſo (eſpecially of the better ſort and condition) who for notorious contumacie or other notable crimes ſtand lawfully excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, (vnleſſe within three moneths im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly after the ſaid ſentence of Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication pronounced againſt them, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme themſelues, and obtaine the benefit of Abſolution) bee euery ſixe moneths enſuing, aſwell in the Pariſh Church, as in the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall Church of the Dioceſſe in which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, by the Miniſter openly in time of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Seruice vpon ſome Sunday denounced and declared Excommunicate, that others may be thereby both admoniſhed to refraine their company and ſociety, and excited the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:152063:89"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:90"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:90"/>
to procure out a Writ <hi>De excommunicate capiendo,</hi> thereby to bring and reduce them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to due order and obedience. Likewiſe the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter of euery Eccleſiaſtical Court, ſhal yeere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly betweene Michaelmas and Chriſtmas, due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly certifie the Archbiſhop of the Prouince of all and ſinguler the premiſſes aforeſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="66" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXVI.</hi> Miuiſters to conferre with Recuſants.</head>
                  <p>EVery Miniſter being a Preacher, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing any Popiſh Recuſant or Recuſants in his Pariſh, and thought fit by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of the Dioceſſe, ſhall labour diligently wi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h them from time to time, thereby to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cl<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ime them from their errours. And if he be <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Preacher, or not ſuch a Preacher, then hee ſhall procure, if he can poſsibly, ſome that are Preachers ſo qualified, to take paines with them for that purpoſe. If he can procure none, then he ſhall informe the Biſhop of the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe thereof, who ſhal not only appoint ſome neighbour Preacher or Preachers adioyning <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> labour vpon them, but himſelfe alſo <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> important affaires wil permit him) ſhal <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> is beſt endeuour by inſtruction, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion,
<pb facs="tcp:152063:91"/>
and all good meanes he can deuiſe to reclaime both them and all other within his Dioceſſe ſo affected.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="67" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXVII.</hi> Miniſters to viſite the ſicke.</head>
                  <p>WHen any perſon is dangerouſly ſicke in any Pariſh, the Miniſter or Curate (hauing knowledge thereof) ſhal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort vnto him or her (if the diſeaſe bee not knowen or probably ſuſpected to bee infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous) to inſtruct and comfort them in their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, according to the order of the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion booke, if he be no Preacher: or if hee be a Preacher, then as he ſhall thinke moſt need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and conuenient. And when any is paſsing out of this life, a Bell ſhall bee tolled, and the Miniſter ſhall not then ſlacke to doe his laſt duetie. And after the parties death (if it ſo fall out) there ſhal be rung no more but one ſhort peale, and one other before the buriall, and one other after the buriall.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="68" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXVIII.</hi> Miniſters not to refuſe to chriſten or bury.</head>
                  <p>NO Miniſter ſhal refuſe or delay t<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> chriſten any child according to the forme of the
<pb facs="tcp:152063:91"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:92"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:92"/>
booke of Common prayer, that is brought to the Church to him vpon Sundayes or Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes to be chriſtened, or to bury any corps that is brought to the Church or Churchyard (conuenient warning being giuen him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of before) in ſuch manner and forme as is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the ſaid booke of Common prayer. And if he ſhall refuſe to chriſten the one, or bury the other, except the party deceaſed were denounced excommunicated <hi>maiori excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municatione,</hi> for ſome grieuous and notorious crime, (and no man able to teſtifie of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance) he ſhalbe ſuſpended by the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe from his Miniſterie by the ſpace of three moneths.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="69" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXIX.</hi> Miniſters not to deferre Chriſtening, if the childe be in danger.</head>
                  <p>IF any Miniſter beeing duely without any maner of colluſion, informed of the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and danger of death of any Infant vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptized in his Pariſh, and thereupon deſired to go or come to the place where the ſaid In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant remaineth to baptize the ſame, ſhal either wilfully refuſe ſo to doe, or of purpoſe, or of
<pb facs="tcp:152063:93"/>
groſſe negligence ſhall ſo deferre the time, as when he might conueniently haue reſorted to the place, and haue baptized the ſaid Infant, it dieth through ſuch his default vnbaptized: the ſaid Miniſter ſhall be ſuſpended for three mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, and before his reſtitution ſhall acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge his fault, and promiſe before his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie, that hee will not wittingly incurre the like againe. Prouided, that where there is a Curate or a Subſtitute, this Conſtitution ſhall not extend to the Parſon or Vicar himſelfe, but to the Curate or Subſtitute preſent.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="70" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXX.</hi> Miniſters to keepe a Regiſter of Chriſtnings, Weddings, and Burials.</head>
                  <p>IN euery Pariſh Church and Chappell with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Realme, ſhall be prouided one parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Booke at the charge of the Pariſh, wherein ſhall be written the day and yeere of euery Chriſtning, Wedding, and Buriall, which haue bene in that Pariſh ſince the time that the Law was firſt made in that behalfe, ſo farre as the ancient Bookes thereof can be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, but eſpecially ſince the beginning of the Raigne of the late Qneene. And for the ſafe
<pb facs="tcp:152063:93"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:94"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:94"/>
keeping of the ſaid booke, the Churchwardens at the charge of the Pariſh, ſhall prouide one ſure Coffer with three lockes &amp; keyes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the one to remaine with the Miniſter, and the other two with the Churchwardens ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, ſo that neither the Miniſter without the two Churchwardens, nor the Churchwardens without the Miniſter, ſhall at any time take that Booke out of the ſaid Coffer. And hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth vpon euery Sabboth day, immediatly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Morning or Euening prayer, the Miniſter and Churchwardens ſhal take the ſaid parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Booke out of the ſaid Coffer, and the Miniſter in the preſence of the Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens ſhall write and record in the ſaid Booke, the names of all perſons Chriſtned, together with the names and ſurnames of their Parents, and alſo the names of all perſons Married and Buried in that pariſh, in the weeke before, and the day and yeere of euery ſuch Chriſtning, Marriage, and Buriall: And that done, they ſhal lay vp that Booke in the Coffer as before: and the Miniſter and Churchwardens vnto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery page of that Booke, when it ſhall be filled with ſuch inſcriptions, ſhall ſubſcribe their
<pb facs="tcp:152063:95" rendition="simple:additions"/>
names. And the Churchwardens ſhall once euery yeere within one Moneth after the fiue and twentieth day of March, tranſmit vnto the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, or his Chancellor, a true Copy of the names of al perſons Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, Married, or Buried in their Pariſh in the yeere before (ended the ſaid fiue and twentieth day of March) and the certaine dayes and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths in which euery ſuch Chriſtning, Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and Buriall was had, to be ſubſcribed with the hands of the ſaid Miniſter &amp; Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, to the end the ſame may faithfully bee preſerued in the Regiſtrie of the ſaid Biſhop: which Certificat ſhalbe receiued without Fee. And if the Miniſter or Churchwardens ſhall be negligent in performance of any thing here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contained, it ſhall be lawfull for the Biſhop or his Chancellor to conuent them, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede againſt euery of them as contemners of this our Conſtitution.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="71" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXXI.</hi> Miniſters not to Preach or adminiſter the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in priuate houſes.</head>
                  <p>NO Miniſter ſhall Preach or adminiſter the holy Communion in any priuate houſe,
<pb facs="tcp:152063:95"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:96" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:96" rendition="simple:additions"/>
except it be in times of neceſsitie, when any being either ſo impotent, as hee cannot goe to the Church, or very dangerouſly ſicke, are deſirous to bee partakers of that holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, vnder paine of ſuſpenſion for the firſt offence, and Excommunication for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond. Prouided that houſes are here reputed for Priuate houſes, wherein are no Chappels dedicated and allowed by the Eccleſiaſticall Lawes of this Realme. And prouided alſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the paine before expreſſed, that no Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leins doe Preach or adminiſter the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in any other places, but in the Chappels of the ſaid houſes, and that alſo they do the ſame very ſeldome vpon Sundayes and holy dayes. So that both the Lords and Maſters of the ſaid houſes and their families ſhall at other times reſort to their owne Pariſh Churches, and there receiue the holy Communion at the leaſt once euery yeere.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="72" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXXII.</hi> Miniſters not to appoint publike or priuate Faſts, or Propheſies, or to exorcize, but by authority.</head>
                  <p>NO Miniſter or Miniſters ſhall without the Licence and direction of the Biſhop of
<pb facs="tcp:152063:97" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the Dioceſſe firſt obtained and had vnder his Hand and Seale, appoint or keepe any ſolemne Faſts, either publikely or in any priuate houſes, other then ſuch as by Law are, or by publike authoritie ſhall be appointed, nor ſhall be wittingly preſent at any of them, vnder paine of Suſpenſion for the firſt fault, of Excommunication for the ſecond, and of Depoſition from the Miniſterie for the third. Neither ſhall any Miniſter not licenſed, as is aforeſaide, preſume to appoint or hold a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny meetings for Sermons, commonly termed by ſome, Propheſies or Exerciſes, in Market townes or other places, vnder the ſaid paines: Nor without ſuch Licenſe to attempt vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pretence whatſoeuer, either of Poſſeſsion or Qbſeſsion, by faſting and prayer to caſt out any deuill or deuils, vnder paine of the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Impoſture, or Coſenage, and Depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Miniſterie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="73" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXXIII.</hi> Miniſters not to hold priuate Conuenticles.</head>
                  <p>FOraſmuch as all Conuenticles and ſecret meetings of Prieſtes and Miniſters, haue bene euer iuſtly accompted very hurtfull
<pb facs="tcp:152063:97"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:98" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:98"/>
to the State of the Church wherein they liue: We doe now ordaine and conſtitute, That no Prieſts or Miniſters of the word of God, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other perſons ſhall meete together in any priuate houſe or elſewhere to conſult vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny matter or courſe to bee taken by them, or vpon their motion or direction by any other, which may any way tend to the impeaching or deprauing of the doctrine of the Church of England, or of the Booke of Common praier, or of any part of the gouernment and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline now eſtabliſhed in the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, vnder pain of Exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication <hi>ipſo facto.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="74" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXXIIII.</hi> Decencie in apparell enioyned to Ministers.</head>
                  <p>THe true, ancient and flourishing Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Chriſt being euer deſirous that their Prelacie and Cleargie might be had as well in outward reuerence, as otherwiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded for the worthineſſe of their Miniſtery, did thinke it fit by a preſcript forme of decent and comely Apparell, to haue them knowen to the people, and thereby to receiue the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and eſtimation due to the ſpecial Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Miniſters of Almighty God. Wee
<pb facs="tcp:152063:99"/>
therefore following their graue iudgement, and the ancient Cuſtome of the Church of England, and hoping that in time new fangle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Apparell in ſome factious perſons will die of it ſelfe, do conſtitute and appoint, That the Archbiſhop and Biſhops, ſhall not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to vſe the accuſtomed Apparel of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees. Likewiſe all Deanes, Maſters of Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, Archdeacons, and Prebendaries in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall and Collegiate Churches, (beeing Prieſts or Deacons) Doctors in Diuinitie, Law, and Phiſicke, Bachelers in Diuinitie, Maſters of Arts, and Bachelers of Lawe hauing any Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall liuing, ſhall vſually weare Gownes with ſtanding collers, and ſleeues ſtreight at the hands, or wide ſleeues as is vſed in the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſities, with Hoods or Tippets of Silke or Sarcenet, and ſquare Caps. And that all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Miniſters, admitted or to be admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that Function, ſhall alſo vſually weare the like Apparell, as is aforeſaid, except Tippets onely. We doe further in like maner ordaine, That all the ſaid Eccleſiaſticall perſons aboue mentioned, ſhall vſually weare in their iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys Cloakes with ſleeues, commonly called
<pb facs="tcp:152063:99"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:100"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:100"/>
Prieſts Cloaks without gards, welts, long But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, or cuts. And no Eccleſiaſtical perſon ſhall weare any Coife, or wrought Nightcap, but onely plaine Nightcaps of blacke ſilke, Satten, or Veluet. In all which particulars concerning the Apparell here preſcribed, our meaning is not to attribute any holineſſe or ſpeciall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe to the ſaid garments, but for decencie, grauitie and order, as is before ſpecified. In pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate houſes, and in their Studies, the ſaid per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Eccleſiaſticall may vſe any comely and Schollerlike Apparel. Prouided, that it be not cut or pinckt, and that in publike they goe not in their Dublet and Hoſe, without Coats or Caſſocks: and alſo that they weare not any light coloured Stockins. Likewiſe poore bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed men and Curats (not being able to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide themſelues long Gownes) may goe in ſhort Gownes, of the faſhion aforeſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="75" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXXV.</hi> Sober conuerſation required in Ministers.</head>
                  <p>NO Eccleſiaſtical perſons ſhal at any time, other then for their honeſt neceſsities, reſort to any Tauernes or Alehouſes, neither ſhall they board or lodge in any ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:152063:101"/>
places. Furthermore, they ſhal not giue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to any baſe or ſeruile labour, or to drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or riot, ſpending their time idlely by day or by night, playing at Dice, Cardes, or Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, or any other vnlawfull game: but at all times conuenient, they ſhall heare or reade ſomewhat of the holy Scriptures, or ſhall oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupie themſelues with ſome other honeſt ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die or exerciſe, alwayes doing the things which ſhall appertaine to honeſtie, and ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring to profit the Church of God, hauing alwayes in minde that they ought to excell all others in puritie of life, and ſhould bee exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to the people to liue well and Chriſtianly vnder paine of Eccleſiaſticall cenſures to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with ſeueritie, according to the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of their offences.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="76" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXXVI.</hi> Ministers at no time to forſake their Calling.</head>
                  <p>NO man being admitted a Deacon or Miniſter, ſhall from thenceforth volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily relinquiſh the ſame, nor afterward vſe himſelfe in the courſe of his life, as a Lay man, vpon paine of Excommunication. And the names of all ſuch men ſo forſaking ther
<pb facs="tcp:152063:101"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:102"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:102"/>
calling, the Church-wardens of the Pariſh where they dwell ſhall preſent to the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, or to the Ordinarie of the place, hauing Epiſcopall Iuriſdiction.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>Schoolemaſters.</head>
               <div n="77" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXXVII.</hi> None to teach Schoole without Licence.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O man ſhal teach either in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Schoole, or priuate houſe, but ſuch as ſhall bee allowed by the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, or Ordinarie of the place vnder his Hand and Seale, being found meete aſwell for his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and dexteritie in teaching, as for ſober and honeſt conuerſation, and alſo for right vnderſtanding of Gods true Religion, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo except he ſhall firſt ſubſcribe to the firſt and third Articles afore mentioned ſimply, and to the two firſt clauſes of the ſecond Article.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="78" type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:103"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXXVIII.</hi> Curats deſirous to teach, to bee licenced before others.</head>
                  <p>IN what Pariſh Church or Chappell ſoeuer there is a Curate which is a Maſter of Arts, or Bacheler of Arts, or is otherwiſe well able to teach youth, and will willingly ſo doe, for the better increaſe of his liuing, and trayning vp of children in Principles of true Religion: We will and ordaine, That a Licence to teach youth of the Pariſh where he ſerueth, be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to none by the Ordinarie of that place, but onely to the ſaide Curate. Prouided al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, That this Conſtitution ſhall not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to any Pariſh or Chappell in countrey Townes, where there is a publike Schoole founded already: In which caſe wee thinke it not meete to allow any to teach Grammer, but onely him that is allowed for the ſaid publike Schoole.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="79" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXXIX.</hi> The duetie of Schoolemasters.</head>
                  <p>ALl Schoolemaſters ſhall teach in Engliſh or Latine, as the children are able to beare, the larger or ſhorter Catechiſme
<pb facs="tcp:152063:103"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:104"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:104"/>
heretofore by publike authoritie ſet foorth. And as often as any Sermon ſhall bee vpon Holy and Feſtiuall dayes, within the Pariſh where they teach, they ſhall bring their Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers to the Church where ſuch Sermon ſhall bee made, and there ſee them quietly and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly behaue themſelues, and ſhall examine them at times conuenient after their returne, what they haue borne away of ſuch Sermons. Vpon other dayes, and at other times they ſhal traine them vp with ſuch ſentences of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, as ſhall bee moſt expedient to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to all godlineſſe: and they ſhall teach the Grammer ſet forth by King HEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RY the eight, and continued in the times of King EDVVARD the ſixt, and Queene ELI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZABETH of noble memory, and none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And if any Schoolemaſter being licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and hauing ſubſcribed, as aforeſaid, ſhall offend in any of the premiſſes, or either ſpeake, write, or teach againſt any thing whereunto he hath formerly ſubſcribed, (if vpon admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition by the Ordinary he do not amend and reforme himſelfe) let him bee ſuſpended from teaching Schoole any longer.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:105"/>
               <head>¶Things appertaining to Churches.</head>
               <div n="80" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXXX.</hi> The great Bible and Booke of Common prayer to be had in euery Church.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Church-wardens or Queſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of euery Church &amp; Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell ſhall at the charge of the Pariſh prouide the Booke of Common prayer lately explaned in ſome few points by his Maieſties authoritie according to the Lawes and his Highneſſe prerogatiue in that behalfe, and that with all conuenient ſpeed, but at the furtheſt within two moneths after the publiſhing of theſe our Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And if any Pariſhes bee yet vnfurniſhed of the Bible of the largeſt volume, or of the Bookes of Homilies allowed by Authoritie: the ſaid Church-wardens ſhall within conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient time prouide the ſame at the like charge of the Pariſh.
<pb facs="tcp:152063:105"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:106"/>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="81" type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:106"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXXXI.</hi> A Font of ſtone for Baptiſme in euery Church.</head>
                  <p>ACcording to a former Conſtitution, too much neglected in many places, wee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point, That there ſhalbe a Font of ſtone in euery Church and Chappell where Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is to be miniſtred: the ſame to bee ſet in the ancient vſuall places. In which onely Font the Miniſter ſhall baptize publikely.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="82" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXXXII.</hi> A decent Communion Table in euery Church.</head>
                  <p>WHereas we haue no doubt but that in all Churches within the Realme of England, conuenient and decent Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles are prouided, and placed for the celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the holy Communion, we appoint that the ſame Tables ſhall from time to time bee kept and repaired in ſufficient and ſeemely manner, and couered in time of diuine Seruice with a Carpet of Silke or other decent ſtuffe thought meet by the Ordinarie of the place, if any queſtion be made of it, and with a faire Linnen cloth at the time of the miniſtration as becommeth that Table, and ſo ſtand, ſauing
<pb facs="tcp:152063:107"/>
when the ſaid holy Communion is to bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred. At which time the ſame ſhall bee placed in ſo good ſort within the Church or Chancell, as thereby the Miniſter may be more conueniently heard of the Communicants in his prayer and miniſtration, and the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicants alſo more conueniently and in more number may communicate with the ſaid Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter: and that the ten Commandements be ſet vpon the Eaſt ende of euery Church and Chappell where the people may beſt ſee and reade the ſame, and other choſen Sentences written vpon the walles of the ſaid Churches and Chappels in places conuenient: and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that a conuenient ſeate bee made for the Miniſter to reade Seruice in. All theſe to bee done at the charge of the Pariſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="83" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXXXIII.</hi> A pulpit to be prouided in euery Church.</head>
                  <p>THe Churchwardens or Queſtmen at the common charge of the Pariſhioners in euery Church, ſhall prouide a comely and decent Pulpit to bee ſet in a conuenient place within the ſame by the diſcretion of the Ordinarie of the place, if any queſtion doe
<pb facs="tcp:152063:107"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:108"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:108"/>
ariſe, and to be there ſeemely kept for the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of Gods word.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="84" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXXXIIII.</hi> A Cheſt for Almes in euery Church.</head>
                  <p>THe Churchwardens ſhall prouide and haue within three moneths after the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of theſe conſtitutions, a ſtrong Cheſt, with a hole in the vpper part thereof, to be prouided at the charge of the Pariſh (if there be none ſuch already prouided) hauing three keyes. Of which one ſhall remaine in the cuſtody of the Parſon, Vicar, or Curat, and the other two in the cuſtody of the Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens for the time beeing, which Cheſt they ſhall ſet and faſten in the moſt conuenient place, to the intent the Pariſhioners may put into it their Almes for their poore neighbours. And the Parſon, Vicar, or Curate ſhall dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently from time to time, and eſpecially when men make their Teſtaments, call vpon, exhort, and mooue their neighbours to conferre, and giue as they may well ſpare to the ſaid Cheſt, declaring vnto them, that whereas heretofore they haue bene diligent to beſtow much ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, otherwiſe then God commaunded,
<pb facs="tcp:152063:109"/>
vpon ſuperſtitious vſes: now they ought at this time to be much more ready to helpe the poore and needy, knowing that to relieue the poore, is a ſacrifice which pleaſeth God: and that alſo whatſoeuer is giuen for their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, is giuen to Chriſt himſelfe, &amp; is ſo accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of him, that he will mercifully reward the ſame. The which Almes and deuotion of the people, the Keepers of the keyes ſhall yeerely, quarterly, or oftner (as need requireth) take out of the Cheſt, and diſtribute the ſame in the preſence of moſt of the Pariſh, or ſixe of the chiefe of them, to bee truely and faithfully deliuered to their moſt poore and needy neighbours.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="85" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXXXV.</hi> Churches to be kept in ſufficient reparations.</head>
                  <p>THe Churchwardens or queſtmen ſhall take care and prouide that the Churches bee well and ſufficiently repaired, and ſo from time to time kept and maintained, that the Windowes bee well glazed, and that the Floores be kept paued, plaine, and euen, and all things there in ſuch an orderly and decent ſort, without duſt, or any thing that may bee
<pb facs="tcp:152063:109"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:110"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:110"/>
either noiſome, or vnſeemely, as beſt becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the houſe of God, and is preſcribed in an Homily to that effect. The like care they ſhall take, that the Churchyards bee well and ſufficiently repaired, fenced, and maintained, with Walles, Railes, or Pales, as haue beene in each place accuſtomed, at their charges vnto whom by Lawe the ſame appertaineth: but eſpecially they ſhall ſee that in euery meeting of the Congregation, peace be well kept, and that all perſons Excommunicated, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, be kept out of the Church.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="86" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXXXVI.</hi> Churches to be ſuruayed, and the decayes certified to the high Commiſsioners.</head>
                  <p>EVery Deane, Deane and Chapter, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon, and others which haue authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to holde Eccleſiaſticall Viſitations by Compoſition, Law or Preſcription, ſhall ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uay the Churches of his or their Iuriſdiction, once in euery three yeeres in his owne perſon, or cauſe the ſame to bee done, and ſhall from time to time within the ſaid three yeeres, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the high Commiſsioners for cauſes Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall, euery yeere of ſuch defects in any
<pb facs="tcp:152063:111"/>
the ſaid Churches, as hee or they doe finde to remaine vnrepaired, and the names and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>names of the parties faultie therein. Vpon which Certificat we deſire that the ſayd high Commiſsioners will <hi>Ex Officio mero</hi> ſend for ſuch parties, and compel them to obey the iuſt and lawfull Decrees of ſuch Eccleſiaſticall Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaries, making ſuch Certificates.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="87" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXXXVII.</hi> A Terrier of Glebelands, and other Poſſeſsions belonging to Churches.</head>
                  <p>WE ordaine that the Archbiſhop and all Biſhops within their ſeuerall Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, ſhall procure (as much as in them lieth) that a true note and Terrier of all the Glebes, Lands, Meadowes, Gardens, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards, Houſes, Stockes, Implements, Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp; portions of Tithes lying out of their Pariſhes which belong to any Parſonage or Vicarage, or rurall Prebend, bee taken by the view of honeſt men in euery Pariſh, by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of the Biſhop, whereof the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to bee one, and bee laid vp in the Biſhops Regiſtrie, there to be for a perpetuall memorie thereof.
<pb facs="tcp:152063:111"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:112"/>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="88" type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:112"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXXXVIII.</hi> Churches not to be prophaned.</head>
                  <p>THe Churchwardens or Queſtmen and their Aſsiſtants ſhall ſuffer no Playes, Feaſts, Banquets, Suppers, Church-ales, Drinkings, temporall Courts or Leetes, Lay-iuries, Muſters, or any other prophane vſage to be kept in the Church, Chappel, or Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, neither the Bels to be rong ſuperſtitiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, vpon Holydayes or Eues, abrogated by the Booke of Common prayer, nor at any other times without good cauſe to be allowed by the Miniſter of the place, and by themſelues.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Churchwardens or Queſtmen, and Side<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men or Aſsiſtants.</head>
               <div n="89" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LXXXIX.</hi> The choiſe of Churchwardens and their accompt.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>L Churchwardens or Queſtmen in euery Pariſh, ſhall bee choſen by the ioynt conſent of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter and the Pariſhioners it it may be. But if they cannot agree vpon ſuch a
<pb facs="tcp:152063:113"/>
choiſe, then the Miniſter ſhall chuſe one, and the Pariſhioners an other, and without ſuch a ioynt or ſeuerall choiſe, none ſhall take vpon them to be Churchwardens, neither ſhal they continue any longer then one yere in that Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, except perhaps they be choſen againe in like manner. And all Churchwardens at the end of their yeere, or within a moneth after at the moſt, ſhall before the Miniſter and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners giue vp a iuſt accompt of ſuch mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney as they haue receiued, and alſo what par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly they haue beſtowed in reparations, and otherwiſe for the vſe of the Church. And laſt of all going out of their Office, they ſhall truely deliuer vp to the Pariſhioners whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer money, or other things of right belonging to the Church or Pariſh, which remaineth in their hands, that it may bee deliuered ouer by them to the next Churchwardens by Bill In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dented.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="90" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XC.</hi> The choyſe of Sidemen and their ioynt Office with Churchwardens.</head>
                  <p>THe Churchwardens or Queſtmen of euery Pariſh, and two or three or moe
<pb facs="tcp:152063:113"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:114"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:114"/>
diſcreet perſons in euery Pariſh to bee choſen for Sidemen or Aſsiſtants, by the Miniſter and Pariſhioners, if they can agree, (otherwiſe to bee appointed by the Ordinarie of the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe) ſhall diligently ſee, that all the Pariſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners duely reſort to their Church vpon all Sundayes and Holy dayes, and there continue the whole time of diuine Seruice: and none to walke or to ſtand idle or talking in the Church, or in the Church-yard, or Church-porch during that time. And all ſuch as ſhall bee found ſlacke or negligent in reſorting to the Church, (hauing no great or vrgent cauſe of abſence) they ſhall earneſtly call vpon them: and after due monition (if they amend not) they ſhall preſent them to the Ordinarie of the place. The choice of which perſons, <hi>viz.</hi> Church-wardens or Queſtmen, Side<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men or Aſsiſtants, ſhall bee yeerely made in Eaſter weeke.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:115" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>¶Pariſh Clearks.</head>
               <div n="91" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XCI.</hi> Pariſh Clearks to be choſen by the Miniſter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O Pariſh Clearke vpon any va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation ſhalbe choſen within the Citie of London, or elſewhere within the Prouince of Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, but by the Parſon or Vicar: or where there is no Parſon or Vicar, by the Miniſter of that place for the time being: Which choice ſhall bee ſignified by the ſaid Miniſter, Vicar, or Parſon, to the Pariſhioners the next Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day following in the time of Diuine Seruice. And the ſaid Clearke ſhalbe of twenty yeeres of age at the leaſt, and knowen to the ſaide Parſon, Vicar or Miniſter to be of honeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, and ſufficient for his Reading, Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and alſo for his competent skil in Singing (if it may be.) And the ſaid Clearks ſo cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, ſhall haue and receiue their ancient Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, without fraude or diminution, either at the handes of the Church-wardens at ſuch times as hath bene accuſtomed, or by their
<pb facs="tcp:152063:115"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:116"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:116"/>
owne collection according to the moſt ancient cuſtome of euery Pariſh.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Eccleſiaſticall Courts belonging to the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops Iuriſdiction.</head>
               <div n="92" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XCII.</hi> None to bee Cited into diuers Courts for probate of the ſame Will.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as many heretofore haue bene by Apparitors both of inferiour Courts, and of the Courts of the Archbiſhops Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiues much diſtracted, and diuerſly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and ſummoned for probate of Willes, or to take adminiſtrations of the goods of perſons dying inteſtate, and are thereby vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and grieued with many cauſeleſſe and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary troubles, moleſtations, and expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: Wee conſtitute and appoint, That all Chancellors, Commiſſaries or Officials, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other exerciſing Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction whatſoeuer, ſhall at the firſt charge with an
<pb facs="tcp:152063:117"/>
othe all perſons called, or voluntarily appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring before them for the probate of any Will, or the Adminiſtration of any goods, whether they know, or (moued by any ſpeciall induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) doe firmely beleeue that the partie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed (whoſe Teſtament or goods depend now in queſtion) had at the time of his or her death, any goods or good debts, in any other Dioceſſe or Dioceſſes, or peculiar Iuriſdiction within that Prouince, then in that wherein the ſaid party died, amounting to the value of fiue pounds. And if the ſaid perſon cited, or volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily appearing before him, ſhall vpon his oath affirme, That hee knoweth, or (as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) firmely beleeueth, that the ſaid party de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed had goods or good debts in any other Dioceſſe or Dioceſſes, or peculiar Iuriſdiction within the ſaid Prouince, to the value afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide, and particularly ſpecifie and declare the ſame: then ſhall he preſently diſmiſſe him, not preſuming to intermeddle with the probate of the ſaid Will, or to grant Adminiſtration of the goods of the party ſo dying Inteſtate: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall hee require or exact any other char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the ſaid parties more then ſuch onely as
<pb facs="tcp:152063:117"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:118"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:118"/>
are due for the Citation, and other Proceſſe had and vſed againſt the ſaid parties, vpon their further contumacie: but ſhal openly and plainely declare and profeſſe, that the ſaide cauſe belongeth to the Prerogatiue of the Archbiſhop of that Prouince, willing and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhing the partie to prooue the ſaid Will, or require Adminiſtration of the ſaid goods in the Court of the ſaid Prerogatiue, and to exhibite before him the ſaide Iudge the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate or adminiſtration vnder the ſeale of the Prerogatiue within forty daies next following. And if any Chancellor, Commiſſary, Official, or other exerciſing Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction whatſoeuer, or any their Regiſter ſhall offend herein, let him be <hi>ipſo facto</hi> ſuſpended from the execution of his Office, not to be abſolued or releaſed vntil he haue reſtored to the party all expences by him layed out contrary to the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the premiſſes: and euery ſuch probate of any Teſtament or adminiſtration of goods ſo granted, ſhall be held voyd and fruſtrate to all effects of the Law whatſoeuer.</p>
                  <p>Furthermore wee charge and enioyne, that the Regiſter of euery inferior Iudge doe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:152063:119" rendition="simple:additions"/>
all difficultie or delay, certifie and informe the Apparitor of the Prerogatiue Court, repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vnto him once a moneth and no oftner, what Executors or Adminiſtrators haue bene by his ſaid Iudge for the incompetencie of his owne Iuriſdiction, diſmiſſed to the ſaid Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue Court within the moneth next before, vnder paine of a moneths ſuſpenſion from the exerciſe of his Office for euery default therein. Prouided, that this Canon or any thing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contained, bee not preiudiciall to any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition betweene the Archbiſhop and any Biſhop or other Ordinary, nor to any inferior Iudge that ſhall graunt any probate of Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or adminiſtration of goods to any party that ſhall voluntarily deſire it, both out of the ſaid inferior Court, and alſo out of the Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue. Prouided likewiſe, that if any man die <hi>In itinere,</hi> the goods that he hath about him at that preſent, ſhall not cauſe his Teſtament or Adminiſtration to be liable vnto the Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue Court.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="93" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XCIII.</hi> The Rate of <hi>Bona notabilia</hi> liable to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue Court.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:119"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:120"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:120"/>
FVrthermore wee decree and ordaine, that no Iudge of the Archbiſhops Prerogatiue ſhall henceforward Cite, or cauſe to be Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Ex officio</hi> any perſon whatſoeuer to any of the aforeſaid intents, vnleſſe hee haue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that the partie deceaſed was at the time of his death poſſeſſed of goods and chattels in ſome other Dioceſſe or Dioceſſes, or peculiar Iuriſdiction within that Prouince then in that wherein hee died, amounting to the value of fiue pounds at the leaſt, decreeing and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that who ſo hath not goods in diuers Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſſes to the ſaid Summe or value, ſhal not be accounted to haue <hi>bona notabilia.</hi> Alwayes prouided, that this clauſe here, and in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Conſtitution mentioned, ſhall not preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice thoſe Dioceſſes where by compoſition or cuſtome <hi>bona notabilia</hi> are rated at a greater ſumme. And if any Iudge of the Prerogatiue Court, or any his Surrogate or his Regiſter or Apparitor, ſhall Cite or cauſe any perſon to be Cited into his Court contrary to the tenor of the premiſſes, he ſhall reſtore to the party ſo Cited all his coſts and charges, and the actes and proceedings in that behalfe ſhall bee held
<pb facs="tcp:152063:121"/>
voide and fruſtrate. Which expences if the ſaid Iudge or Regiſter or Apparitor ſhal refuſe accordingly to pay, he ſhalbe ſuſpended from the exerciſe of his Office vntill he yeeld to the performance thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="94" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XCIIII.</hi> None to be Cited into the Arches or Audience but dwellers within the Archbiſhops Dioceſse or Peculiars.</head>
                  <p>NO Deane of the Arches nor Officiall of the Archbiſhops Conſiſtory, nor any Iudge of the Audience, ſhall hencefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in his own name or in the name of the Archbiſhop either <hi>ex Officio</hi> or at the inſtance of any party, originally Cite, Summon, or any way compell, or procure to be Cited, Summo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or compelled, any perſon which dwelleth not within the particular Dioceſſe or Peculiar of the ſaid Archbiſhop, to appeare before him or any of them for any cauſe or matter what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer belonging to Eccleſiaſtical cognizance, without the Licence of the Dioceſan firſt had and obtained in that behalfe, other then in ſuch particular caſes onely as are expreſly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted and reſerued in and by a Statute <hi>Anno</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:121"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:122"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:122"/>
23. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. And if any of the ſaid Iudges ſhall, offend herein, he ſhall for euery ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence be ſuſpended from the exerciſe of his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for the ſpace of three whole moneths.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="95" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XCV.</hi> The reſtraint of double Quarrels.</head>
                  <p>ALbeit by former Conſtitutions of the Church of England, euery Biſhop hath had two moneths ſpace to inquire and informe himſelfe of the ſufficiencie, and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of euery Miniſter, after he hath bene pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented vnto him to bee inſtituted into any Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice: yet for the auoiding of ſome inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences, wee doe now abridge and reduce the ſaid two moneths vnto eight &amp; twenty dayes onely. In reſpect of which abridgement, wee doe ordaine &amp; appoint, that no double Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell ſhal hereafter be granted out of any of the Archbiſhops Courts at the ſuite of any Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter whoſoeuer, except hee ſhall firſt take his perſonall oath, that the ſaid eight and twentie dayes at the leaſt are expired, after he firſt ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered his preſentation to the Biſhop, and that he refuſed to grant him Inſtitution thereupon: or ſhall enter bonds with ſufficient ſureties to
<pb facs="tcp:152063:123" rendition="simple:additions"/>
prooue the ſame to be true, vnder paine of ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion of the Granter thereof from the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of his Office, for halfe a yeere <hi>toties quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> to be denounced by the ſaid Archbiſhop, and Nullitie of the double Quarrell aforeſaid, ſo vnduely procured, to all intents and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes whatſoeuer. Alwayes prouided that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſaid eight and twentie daies, the Biſhop ſhall not inſtitute any other to the preiudice of the ſaid partie before preſented, <hi>ſub poena nullitatis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="96" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XCVI.</hi> Inhibitions not to be granted without the ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an Aduocate.</head>
                  <p>THat the Iuriſdictions of Biſhops may be preſerued (as neere as may be) entier and free from preiudice, and that for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoofe of the Subiects of this land, better pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſon be made that henceforward they be not grieued with friuolous and wrongfull ſuits and moleſtations: It is ordained and prouided that no Inhibition ſhall bee graunted out of any Court, belonging to the Archbiſhop of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury at the inſtance of any partie, vnleſſe it be ſubſcribed by an Aduocate practiſing in the
<pb facs="tcp:152063:123"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:124" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:124" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſaid Court: which the ſaid Aduocate ſhal doe freely, not taking any Fee for the ſame, except the partie proſecuting the ſuit, doe voluntarily beſtow ſome gratuity vpon him for his counſel and aduice in the ſaid cauſe. The like courſe ſhall be vſed in graunting foorth any Inhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at the inſtance of any party by the Biſhop or his Chancellor againſt the Archdeacon, or any other perſon exerciſing Eccleſiaſticall Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction: and if in the Court or Conſiſtorie of any Biſhop there be no aduocate at all, then ſhall the ſubſcription of a Proctor practiſing in the ſame Court be held ſufficient.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="97" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XCVII.</hi> Inhibitions not to be graunted vntill the Appeale be exhibited to the Iudge.</head>
                  <p>IT is further ordered &amp; decreed, that hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward no Inhibition be granted by occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of any interlocutory decree, or in any cauſe of correction whatſoeuer, except vnder the forme aforeſaid: and moreouer that before the going out of any ſuch Inhibition, the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale it ſelfe, or a copie thereof (auouched by oath to be iuſt and true) bee exhibited to the
<pb facs="tcp:152063:125"/>
Iudge, or his lawfull Surrogate, whereby hee may be fully informed, both of the qualitie of the crime, and of the cauſe of the grieuance, before the granting foorth of the ſaid inhibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And euery Appellant or his lawfull Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor ſhal before the obteining of any ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition, ſhew and exhibite to the Iudge or his Surrogate in writing, a true copy of thoſe Acts wherewith hee complaineth himſelfe to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grieued, and from which he appealeth, or ſhal take a corporall oath that hee hath performed his diligence, &amp; true endeuor for the obteining of the ſame, &amp; could not obtein it at the hands of the Regiſter in the Country, or his Deputy, tendring him his Fee. And if any Iudge or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter ſhall either procure or permit any Inhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition to be ſealed, ſo as is ſaid, contrary to the forme &amp; limitation aboue ſpecified, let him be ſuſpended from the execution of his office, for the ſpace of three moneths: If any Proctor, or other perſon whatſoeuer by his appointment, ſhall offend in any of the premiſſes, either by making or ſending out any Inhibition, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the tenour of the ſaid premiſſes, let him be remoued from the exerciſe of his Office for
<pb facs="tcp:152063:125"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:126"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:126"/>
the ſpace of a whole yeere without hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe or reſtoring.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="98" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XCVIII.</hi> Inhibitions not to bee granted to factious Appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants, vnleſse they first ſubſcribe.</head>
                  <p>FOraſmuch as they who breake the Lawes, cannot in reaſon claime any benefite or protection by the ſame: Wee decree and appoint, that after any Iudge Eccleſiaſticall hath proceeded Iudicially againſt obſtinate and factious perſons, and contemners of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, for not obſeruing the Rites and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Church of England, or for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Publike prayer, no Iudge <hi>ad quem,</hi> ſhall admit or allow any his or their Appeales, vnleſſe he hauing firſt ſeene the originall Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale, the partie appellant doe firſt perſonally promiſe and auow, that he wil faithfully keepe and obſerue all the Rites and Ceremonies of the Church of England, as alſo the preſcript fourme of Common prayer: and doe likewiſe ſubſcribe to the three Articles formerly by vs ſpecified and declared.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="99" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>XCIX.</hi> None to marry within the degrees prohibited.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:127"/>NO perſons ſhall marrie within the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees prohibited by the Lawes of God and expreſſed in a Table ſet forth by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie in the yeere of our Lord God 1563. and all marriages ſo made &amp; contacted ſhall bee adiudged inceſtuous and vnlawfull, and conſequently ſhall be diſſolued as voyd from the beginning, and the parties ſo married ſhall by courſe of Law be ſeparated. And the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Table ſhall be in euery Church publikely ſet vp and fixed at the charge of the Pariſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="100" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>C.</hi> None to marrie vnder xxj. yeeres, without their Parents conſent.</head>
                  <p>NO children vnder the age of one and twentie yeeres complete, ſhall contract themſelues, or marrie without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of their Parents, or of their Guardians and Gouernours, if their Parents be deceaſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="101" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CI.</hi> By whom Licences to marrie without Bannes ſhal be granted, and to what ſort of perſons.</head>
                  <p>NO Facultie or Licence ſhalbe henceforth granted for ſolemnization of Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie betwixt any parties, without thrice
<pb facs="tcp:152063:127"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:128"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:128"/>
open publication of the Bannes according to the booke of Common prayer, by any perſon exerciſing any Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction, or claiming any Priuiledges in the right of their Churches: but the ſame ſhalbe granted onely by ſuch as haue Epiſcopall authoritie, or the Commiſſary for Faculties, Vicars generall of the Archbiſhops and Biſhops <hi>ſede plena,</hi> or <hi>ſede vacante,</hi> the Guardian of the Spiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties or Ordinaries exerciſing of right Epiſcopal Iuriſdiction in their ſeuerall Iuriſdictions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectiuely, and vnto ſuch perſons onely as bee of good ſtate and qualitie, and that vpon good caution and ſecuritie taken.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="102" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CII.</hi> Securitie to be taken at the graunting of ſuch Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cences, and vnder what conditions.</head>
                  <p>THe ſecuritie mentioned ſhall containe theſe conditions: Firſt, that at the time of the granting euery ſuch Licence, there is not any impediment of precontract, conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinitie, affinitie, or other lawfull cauſe to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſaid marriage. Secondly, that there is not any controuerſie or ſuit depending in any Court before any Eccleſiaſticall Iudge touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:152063:129" rendition="simple:additions"/>
any contract or marriage of either of the ſaid parties with any other. Thirdly, that they haue obtained thereunto the expreſſe conſent of their parents (if they be liuing) or otherwiſe of their Guardians or Gouernours. Laſtly, that they ſhall celebrate the ſaid Matrimonie pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely in the Pariſh Church or Chappell where one of them dwelleth, and in no other place, and that betweene the houres of eight and twelue in the forenoone.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="103" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CIII.</hi> Oathes to be taken for the conditions.</head>
                  <p>FOr the auoiding of all fraud and colluſion in the obtaining of ſuch Licences &amp; Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations: We further conſtitute and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point, That before any Licence for the Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of Matrimonie, without publication of Bannes be had or granted, it ſhall appeare to the Iudge by the oathes of two ſufficient witneſſes, one of them to be knowen either to the Iudge himſelfe, or to ſome other perſon of good reputation then preſent, and knowen likewiſe to the ſaid Iudge, that the expreſſe conſent of the Parents, or Parent if one bee dead, or Gardians, or Gardian of the parties is
<pb facs="tcp:152063:129"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:130"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:130" rendition="simple:additions"/>
thereunto had and obtained. And further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more that one of the parties perſonally ſweare, that he beleeueth there is no let or impediment of precontract, kindred, or alliance, or of any other lawfull cauſe whatſoeuer, nor any ſuite commenced in any Eccleſiaſticall Court, to bar or hinder the proceeding of the ſaid Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie, according to the tenour of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Licence.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="104" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CIIII.</hi> An exception of thoſe that are in Widowhood.</head>
                  <p>IF both the parties which are to marry being in Widowhood, do ſeeke a Facultie for the forbearing of Bannes, then the clauſes before mentioned, requiring the Parents conſents, may be omitted: but the Pariſhes where they dwell both ſhall be expreſſed in the Licence, as alſo the Pariſh named where the Marriage ſhall be celebrated. And if any Commiſſary for Faculties, Vicars generall, or other the ſaid Ordinaries ſhal offend in the premiſſes, or any part thereof, he ſhall for euery time ſo offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, be ſuſpended from the execution of his Office for the ſpace of ſixe moneths: and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuch Licence or diſpenſation ſhall be held
<pb facs="tcp:152063:131" rendition="simple:additions"/>
voyd to al effects and purpoſes, as if there had neuer bene any ſuch granted: and the parties marrying by vertue thereof, ſhall bee ſubiect to the puniſhments which are appointed for Clandeſtine Marriages.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="105" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CV.</hi> No Sentence for Diuorce to bee giuen vpon the ſole confeſsion of the parties.</head>
                  <p>FOraſmuch as Matrimoniall cauſes haue bene alwayes reckoned and reputed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the weightieſt, and therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the greater caution when they come to be handled and debated in Iudgement, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in cauſes wherein Matrimonie hauing bene in the Church duely ſolemnized, is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon any ſuggeſtion or pretext whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to bee diſſolued or annulled: Wee doe ſtraightly charge and inioyne, that in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings to Diuorce and Nullities of Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, good circumſpection and aduice bee vſed, and that the trueth may (as farre as is poſsible) bee ſifted out by the depoſition of witneſſes , and oth<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> lawfull proofes and eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and that credit be not giuen to the ſole confeſsion of the parties themſelues, howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
<pb facs="tcp:152063:131"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:132"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:132" rendition="simple:additions"/>
taken vpon oath, either within or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Court.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="106" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CVI.</hi> No Sentence for Diuorce to be giuen but in open Court.</head>
                  <p>NO Sentence ſhall be giuen either for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration <hi>à thoro &amp; menſa,</hi> or for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulling of pretended Matrimonie, but in open Court, and in the ſeat of Iuſtice, and that with the knowledge and conſent either of the Archbiſhop within his Prouince, or of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop within his Dioceſſe, or of the Deane of the Arches, the Iudge of the Audience of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury, or of the Vicars general, or other prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Officials, or <hi>ſede vacante,</hi> of the Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians of the Spiritualties, or other Ordinaries to whom of right it apperteineth, in their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Iuriſdictions and Courts, and concerning them onely that are then dwelling vnder their Iuriſdictions.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="107" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CVII.</hi> In all Sentences for Diuorce, bond to be taken for not marrying, during each others life.</head>
                  <p>IN all Sentences pronounced onely for Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorce and Separation, <hi>à thoro &amp; menſa,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:133"/>
there ſhall bee a caution and reſtraint inſerted in the Act of the ſaid Sentence, That the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſo ſeparated, ſhal liue chaſtly &amp; continent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: neither ſhall they, during each others life, contract Matrimonie with any other perſon. And for the better obſeruing of this laſt clauſe, the ſaid Sentence of Diuorce ſhall not be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, vntill the partie or parties requiring the ſame, haue giuen good and ſufficient cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; ſecuritie into the Court, that they will not any way breake or trangreſſe the ſaid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint or prohibition.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="108" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CVIII.</hi> The penaltie for Iudges offending in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſses.</head>
                  <p>ANd if any Iudge giuing Sentence of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorce or Separation, ſhall not fully keepe and obſerue the premiſſes, he ſhall be by the Archibiſhop of the Prouince, or by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of the Dioceſſe, ſuſpended from the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of his Office for the ſpace of a whole yere, and the Sentence of Separation ſo giuen con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the forme aforeſaid, ſhal be held voyd to all intents and purpoſes of the Law, as if it had not at all bene giuen or pronounced.
<pb facs="tcp:152063:133"/>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:134"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:134"/>
               <head>¶Eccleſiaſtical Courts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Iuriſdiction of Biſhops and Archdeacons, and <hi>the proceedings in</hi> them.</head>
               <div n="109" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CIX.</hi> Notorious Crimes and Scandals to be certified in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Eccleſiasticall Courts by preſentment.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F any offend their brethren, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Adulterie, whoredome, Inceſt, or Drunkenneſſe, or by Swearing, Ribaldrie, Vſurie, or any other vncleanneſſe and wickedneſſe of life, the Church-wardens or Queſtmen and Sidemen in their next Preſentments to their Ordinaries, ſhall faithfully preſent all and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the ſaid offenders, to the intent that they and euery of them may bee puniſhed by the ſeueritie of the Lawes, according to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, and ſuch notorious offendours ſhall not be admitted to the holy Communion till they be reformed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="110" type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:135"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CX.</hi> Schiſmaticks to be preſented.</head>
                  <p>IF the Churchwardens or Queſtmen or Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtants, doe or ſhall know any man within their Pariſh or elſewhere, that is a hinderer of the word of God to bee read or ſincerely Preached, or of the execution of theſe our Conſtitutions, or a fautor of any vſurped or forreine power by the Lawes of this Realme iuſtly reiected and taken away, or a defender of Popiſh and erroneous doctrine: they ſhall detect and preſent the ſame to the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe or Ordinarie of the place, to bee cenſured &amp; puniſhed, according to ſuch Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Lawes as are preſcribed in that behalfe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="111" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXI.</hi> Diſturbers of diuine Seruice to be preſented.</head>
                  <p>IN all Viſitations of Biſhops and Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, the Churchwardens or Queſtmen and Sidemen ſhall truely and perſonally preſent the names of all thoſe, which behaue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues rudely or diſorderly in the Church, or which by vntimely ringing of Bels, by walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, talking, or other noyſe ſhall hinder the Miniſter or Preacher.
<pb facs="tcp:152063:135"/>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="112" type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:136"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:136"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXII.</hi> Not Communicants at Easter to be preſented.</head>
                  <p>THe Miniſter, Church-wardens, Queſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men &amp; Aſsiſtants of euery Pariſh church and Chappell, ſhall yeerely within fortie daies after Eaſter exhibite to the Biſhop or his Chancellor, the names and ſurnames of all the Pariſhioners, aſwell men as women, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the age of ſixteene yeeres, receiued not the Communion at Eaſter before.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="113" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXIII.</hi> Miniſters may preſent.</head>
                  <p>BEcauſe it often commeth to paſſe that the Churchwardens, Sidemen, Queſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and ſuch other perſons of the Laytie as are to take care for the ſuppreſsing of ſinne and wickedneſſe in their ſeuerall Pariſhes, as much as in them lieth, by admonition, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion &amp; denunciation to their Ordinaries, doe forbeare to diſcharge their duties therein, either through feare of their Superiours, or through negligence, more then were fit, the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſſe of theſe times conſidered: Wee ordaine, That hereafter euery Parſon and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car, or in the lawfull abſence of any Parſon or
<pb facs="tcp:152063:137"/>
Vicar, then their Curates and Subſtitutes may ioyne in euery preſentment with the ſayde Churchwardens, Sidemen, and the reſt aboue mentioned at the times hereafter limited, if they the ſaid Churchwardens and the reſt will preſent ſuch enormities as are apparant in the Pariſh: or if they wil not, then euery ſuch Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Vicar, or in their abſence as aforeſaid their Curates may themſelues preſent to their Ordinaries at ſuch times, and when elſe they thinke it meete, all ſuch crimes as they haue in charge, otherwiſe, as by them (being the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that ſhould haue the chiefe care for the ſuppreſsing of ſinne and impiety in their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes) ſhall be thought to require due refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. Prouided alwayes, that if any man confeſſe his ſecret and hidden ſins to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter for the vnburthening of his conſcience, and to receiue ſpiritual conſolation and eaſe of minde from him, We do not any way binde the ſaid Miniſter by this our Conſtitution, but do ſtraightly charge and admoniſh him, that he do not at any time reueale &amp; make know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to any perſon whatſoeuer, any crime or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence ſo committed to his truſt and ſecrecie
<pb facs="tcp:152063:137"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:138" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:138" rendition="simple:additions"/>
(except they bee ſuch crimes as by the Lawes of this Realme, his owne life may be called in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to queſtion for concealing the ſame) vnder paine of irregularitie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="114" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXIIII.</hi> Miniſters ſhall preſent Recuſants.</head>
                  <p>EVery Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, ſhall care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully informe themſelues euery yere here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, how many Popiſh Recuſants, men, women &amp; children aboue the age of thirteene yeeres, and how many being popiſhly giuen (who though they come to the Church, yet doe refuſe to receiue the Communion) are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, or make their abode either as So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iourners or common Gueſts in any of their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Pariſhes, and ſhall ſet downe their true names in writing (if they can learne them) or otherwiſe ſuch names as for the time they ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, diſtinguiſhing the abſolute Recuſants from halfe Recuſants: and the ſame ſo farre as they know or beleeue ſo diſtinguiſhed &amp; ſet downe vnder their hands, ſhall truely preſent to their Ordinaries before the Feaſt of the Natiuitie next enſuing, vnder paine of ſuſpenſion to bee inflicted vpon them by their ſaid Ordinaries,
<pb facs="tcp:152063:139" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and ſo euery yeere hereafter vpon the like paine, before the Feaſt of S. Iohn Baptiſt. Alſo we ordaine, that all ſuch Ordinaries, Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, Commiſſaries, Archdeacons, Officials, and all other Eccleſiaſticall Officers, to whom the ſaid preſentments ſhall be exhibited, ſhall likewiſe within one moneth after the receit of the ſame, vnder paine of ſuſpenſion by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop from the execution of their Offices for the ſpace of halfe a yere (as often as they ſhall offend therein) deliuer them or cauſe to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered to the Biſhop reſpectiuely: who ſhall alſo exhibite them to the Archbiſhop within ſixe weekes, and the Archbiſhop to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie within other ſixe weekes after he hath receiued the ſaid preſentments.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="115" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXV.</hi> Miniſters and Churchwardens not to bee ſued for Preſenting.</head>
                  <p>WHereas for the reformation of crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous perſons and diſorders in euery Pariſh, the Churchwardens, Queſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Sidemen, and ſuch other Church Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers are ſworne, and the Miniſter charged to preſent as well the crimes and diſorders com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb facs="tcp:152063:139"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:140"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:140"/>
by the ſaid criminous perſons, as alſo the common fame which is ſpread abroad of them, whereby they are often maligned and ſometimes troubled by the ſaid Delinquents or their friends: We doe admoniſh and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort all Iudges both Eccleſiaſticall and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, as they regard and reuerence the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full iudgement ſeate of the higheſt Iudge, that they admit not in any of their Courts, any complaint, plea, ſuit, or ſuits, againſt any ſuch Churchwarden, Queſtmen, Sidemen, or other Church officers for making any ſuch preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, nor againſt any Miniſter for any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment that hee ſhall make: all the ſaid pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments tending to the reſtraint of ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe impietie, and conſidering that the rules both of Charitie and Gouernment doe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume that they did nothing therein of malice, but for the diſcharge of their conſciences.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="116" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXVI.</hi> Churchwardens not bound to Preſent oftner then twice a yeere.</head>
                  <p>NO Churchwardens, Queſtmen, or Side<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of any Pariſh, ſhall bee inforced to exhibite their preſentments to any ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="tcp:152063:141" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction aboue once in euery yeere, where it hath bene no oftner vſed, nor aboue twiſe in any Dioceſſe whatſoeuer, except it be at the Biſhops Viſitation. For the which preſentments of euery Pariſh Church or Chappell, the Regiſter of any Court where they are to be exhibited, ſhall not receiue in one yeere aboue foure pence, vnder paine for euery offence therein, of ſuſpenſion from the execution of his Office for the ſpace of a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <hi>toties quoties.</hi> Prouided alwayes that as good occaſion ſhall require, it ſhall be lawfull for euery Miniſter, Churchwardens, and Side<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to preſent offenders as oft as they ſhall thinke meete. And likewiſe for any godly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed perſon, or for any Eccleſiaſticall Iudge, vpon knowledge or notice giuen vnto him or them of any enormious crime within his Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, to moue the Miniſter, Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, or Sidemen, as they tender the glory of God and reformation of ſinne, to preſent the ſame, if they ſhall finde ſufficient cauſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them thereunto, that it may bee in due time puniſhed and reformed. Prouided that for theſe voluntarie preſentments, there be no
<pb facs="tcp:152063:141"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:142"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:142"/>
Fee required or taken of them, vnder the paine aforeſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="117" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXVII.</hi> Churchwardens not to be troubled for not preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting oftner then twiſe a yeere.</head>
                  <p>NO Churchwardens, Queſtmen, or Side<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhall be called or cited, but onely at the ſaid time or times before limited, to appeare before any Eccleſiaſticall Iudge who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, for refuſing at other times to preſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny faults committed in their Pariſhes, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable by Eccleſiaſticall lawes. Neither ſhall they nor any of them after their preſentments exhibited at any of thoſe times be any further troubled for the ſame, except vpon manif<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt and euident proofe it may appeare that they did then willingly and wittingly omit to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſome ſuch publike crime or crimes as they knew to be committed, or could not be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that there was then a publike fame of them, or vnleſſe there be very iuſt cauſe to call them for the explanation of their former pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments. In which caſe of wilfull omiſsion, their Ordinaries ſhall proceed againſt them in ſuch ſort as in cauſes of wilfull periury in a
<pb facs="tcp:152063:143" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Court Eccleſiaſticall it is alreadie by Law pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="118" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXVIII.</hi> The old Churchwardens to make their Preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments before the new be ſworne.</head>
                  <p>THe office of al Churchwardens and Side<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhall bee reputed euer hereafter to continue vntill the new Churchwardens that ſhall ſucceed them, be ſworne, which ſhal be the firſt weeke after Eaſter, or ſome weeke following, according to the direction of the Ordinary. Which time ſo appointed, ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes be one of the two times in euery yeere, when the Miniſter and Churchwardens, and Sidemen of euery Pariſh ſhall exhibite to their ſeuerall Ordinaries, the preſentments of ſuch enormities as haue happened in their Pariſhes ſince their laſt preſentments. And this duetie they ſhall performe before the newly choſen Churchwardens and Sidemen be ſworne, and ſhall not be ſuffered to paſſe ouer the ſaid pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments to thoſe that are newly come into office, and are by intendment ignorant of ſuch crimes, vnder paine of thoſe cenſures which are appointed for the reformation of ſuch dalliers
<pb facs="tcp:152063:143"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:144"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:144"/>
and diſpenſers with their owne conſciences and oathes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="119" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXIX.</hi> Conuenient time to be aſsigned for framing Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments.</head>
                  <p>FOr the auoyding of ſuch inconueniences as heretofore haue happened by the haſty making of Billes of Preſentments, vpon the dayes of the Viſitation and Synods: it is ordered, That alwayes hereafter euery Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, Archdeacon, Commiſſary, and Offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and euery other perſon hauing Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Iuriſdiction at the ordinary time when the Churchwardens are ſworne: and the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and Biſhops when he or they doe ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon their Viſitation, ſhall deliuer, or cauſe to be deliuered to the Churchwardens, Queſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Sidemen of euery Pariſh, or to ſome of them, ſuch Bookes of Articles as they or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them ſhall require for the yeere follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſaid Churchwardens, Queſtmen, and Sidemen to ground their Preſentments vpon at ſuch times as they are to exhibite them. In which Booke ſhall be contained the forme of the oath which muſt be taken immediatly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:152063:145"/>
euery ſuch Preſentment: to the intent that hauing before hand time ſufficient, not onely to peruſe and conſider what their ſayd oath ſhalbe, but the Articles alſo whereupon they are to ground their Preſentments, they may frame them at home both aduiſedly and truely to the diſcharge of their owne conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, after they are ſworne, as becommeth honeſt and godly men.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="120" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXX.</hi> None to bee Cited into Eccleſiaſticall Courts by Proceſse of <hi>Quorum nomina.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>NO Biſhop, Chancellor, Archdeacon, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall or other Eccleſiaſticall Iudge, ſhall ſuffer any generall Proceſſes of <hi>Quorum nomina,</hi> to bee ſent out of his Court: except the names of all ſuch as thereby are to be cited, ſhalbe firſt expreſly entred by the hand of the Regiſter, or his Deputie, vnder the ſaid Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, and the ſayd Proceſſes and names be firſt ſubſcribed by the Iudge, or his Deputie, and his Seale thereto affixed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="121" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXXI.</hi> None to bee Cited into ſeuerall Courts for one crime.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:145"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:146"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:146"/>IN places where the Biſhop and Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, doe by preſcription or compoſition vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite at ſeuerall times in one and the ſame yeere, leaſt for one and the ſelfe ſame fault any of his Maieſties Subiects ſhould bee challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged &amp; moleſted in diuers Eccleſiaſtical Courts We order and appoint, That euery Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, or his Officiall, within one moneth after the Viſitation ended that yeere, and the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments receiued, ſhall certifie vnder his Hand and Seale, to the Biſhop or his Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, the names and Crimes of all ſuch as are detected and preſented in his ſaid Viſitation, to the end the Chancellor ſhall thencefoorth forbeare to conuent any perſon for any Crime or cauſe ſo detected or preſented to the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon. And the Chancellor within the like time after the Biſhops Viſitation ended, and Preſentments receiued, ſhall vnder his Hand and Seale ſignifie to the Archdeacon or his Official, the names and Crimes of all ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which ſhall be detected or preſented vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him in that Viſitation, to the ſame intent as is aforeſaid. And if theſe Officers ſhall not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie each other as is here preſcribed, or after
<pb facs="tcp:152063:147"/>
ſuch certificate ſhall intermeddle with the crimes or perſons detected and preſented in each others Viſitation: then euery of them ſo offending ſhall be ſuſpended from all exerciſe of his Iuriſdiction, by the Biſhop of the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, vntill he ſhall repay the coſts and expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which the parties grieued haue bene at by that vexation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="122" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXXII.</hi> No ſentence of depriuation or depoſition to bee pronounced againſt a Miniſter, but by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop.</head>
                  <p>WHen any Miniſter is complained of in any Eccleſiaſticall Court belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to any Biſhop of this Prouince for any Crime, the Chancellor, Commiſſarie, Officiall or any other hauing Eccleſiaſtical Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction to whom it ſhall appertaine, ſhal ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedite the cauſe by Proceſſes and other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings againſt him: and vpon contumacie for not appearing, ſhal firſt ſuſpend him, &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward his contumacie continuing, Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate him. But if he appeare and ſubmit himſelfe to the courſe of Law, then the matter being ready for Sentence, and the merits of his
<pb facs="tcp:152063:147"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:148"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:148"/>
offence exacting by Law, either depriuation from his liuing, or depoſition from the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, no ſuch ſentence ſhall bee pronounced by any perſon whatſoeuer, but only by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, with the aſsiſtance of his Chancellor, the Deane, (if they may conueniently bee had) and ſome of the Prebendaries, if the Court be kept neere the Cathedrall Church, or of the Archdeacon if he may bee had conueniently, and two other at the leaſt graue Miniſters and Preachers to be called by the Biſhop, when the Court is kept in other places.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="123" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXXIII.</hi> No Act to be ſped but in open Court.</head>
                  <p>NO Chancellor, Commiſſary, Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, Officiall, or any other perſon vſing Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction whoſoeuer, ſhall ſpeed any iudiciall Act, either of conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious or voluntary Iuriſdiction, except he haue the ordinary Regiſter of that Court, or his lawfull Deputy: or if hee or they will not, or cannot be preſent, then ſuch perſons as by law are allowed in that behalfe to write or ſpeede the ſame, vnder paine of ſuſpenſion <hi>ipſo facto.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="124" type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:149"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXXIIII.</hi> No Court to haue more then one Seale.</head>
                  <p>NO Chancellor, Commiſſarie, Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, Official, or any other exerciſing Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction, ſhal without the Biſhops conſent haue any mo Seales then one for the Sealing of all matters incident to his Office. Which Seale ſhall alwayes be kept ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by himſelfe, or by his lawfull Subſtitute exerciſing Iuriſdiction for him, and remaining within the Iuriſdiction of the ſaid Iudge, or in the Citie or principall Towne of the Countie. This Seale ſhall containe the title of that Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction which euery of the ſaid Iudges or their Deputies doe execute.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="125" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXXV.</hi> Conuenient places to bee choſen for the keeping of Courts.</head>
                  <p>ALl Chancellors, Commiſſaries, Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, Officials, and all other exerciſing Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction, ſhall appoint ſuch meete places for the keeping of their Courts by the aſsignement or approbation of the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, as ſhall bee conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for entertainement of thoſe that are to
<pb facs="tcp:152063:149"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:150"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:150"/>
make their appearance there, and moſt indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent for their trauell. And likewiſe they ſhall keepe and end their Courts in ſuch conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent time, as euery man may returne home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in as due ſeaſon as may be.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="126" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXXVI.</hi> Peculiar and inferiour Courts to exhibite the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall copies of Willes into the Biſhops Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie.</head>
                  <p>WHereas Deanes, Archdeacons, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendaries, Parſons, Vicars, &amp; others exerciſing Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction, claime libertie to proue the laſt Willes &amp; Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaments of perſons deceaſed within their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Iuriſdictions, hauing no knowen nor certaine Regiſters, nor publike place to keepe their Records in, by reaſon whereof many Willes, Rights, and Legacies vpon the death or change of ſuch perſons and their priuate Notaries, miſcarry and cannot bee found, to the great preiudice of his Maieſties Subiects: We therefore order and inioyne, that all ſuch Poſſeſſours &amp; Exerciſers of peculiar Iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhall once in euery yeere exhibite into the publike Regiſtrie of the Biſhop of the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:152063:151"/>
or of the Deane &amp; Chapter vnder whoſe Iuriſdiction the ſaid Peculiars are, euery origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Teſtament of euery perſon in that time deceaſed and by them proued in their ſeuerall peculiar Iuriſdictions, or a true Copie of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuch Teſtament examined, ſubſcribed, and ſealed by the peculiar Iudge and his Notarie. Otherwiſe if any of them faile ſo to doe, the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe or Deane and Chapter vnto whom the ſaid Iuriſdictions doe reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiuely belong, ſhall ſuſpend the ſaid parties and euery of them from the exerciſe of all ſuch peculiar Iuriſdiction, vntill they haue perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med this our Conſtituion.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Iudges Eccleſiaſticall and their Surrogates.</head>
               <div n="127" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXXVII.</hi> The qualitie and oath of Iudges.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O man ſhall hereafter be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Chancellor, Commiſſary, or Official, to exerciſe any Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Iuriſdiction, except hee be of the full age of ſixe and twentie yeeres at
<pb facs="tcp:152063:151"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:152"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:152"/>
the leaſt, and one that is learned in the Ciuill and Eccleſiaſticall Lawes, and is at the leaſt a Maſter of Arts, or Bachelor of Law, and is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably well practiſed in the courſe thereof, as likewiſe well affected, and zealouſly bent to Religion, touching whoſe life and maners no euill example is had, &amp; except before he enter into or execute any ſuch Office, hee ſhall take the oath of the Kings Supremacie in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Biſhop, or in the open Court, and ſhall ſubſcribe to the Articles of Religion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed vpon in the Conuocation in the yeere one thouſand fiue hundred ſixtie and two, and ſhall alſo ſweare that he will to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of his vnderſtanding, deale vprightly and iuſtly in his Office, without reſpect or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of reward: the ſaid oathes and ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be recorded by a Regiſter then preſent. And likewiſe all Chancellors, Commiſſaries, Officials, Regiſters, and all other that do now poſſeſſe or execute any places of Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction, or Seruice, ſhall before Chriſtmas next in the preſence of the Archbiſhop or Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, or in open Court, vnder whom or where they exerciſe their Offices, take the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:152063:153"/>
oathes and ſubſcribe as before is ſaid: or vpon refuſall ſo to doe, ſhall be ſuſpended from the execution of their Offices, vntill they ſhal take the ſaid oathes, and ſubſcribe as aforeſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="128" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXXVIII.</hi> The qualitie of Surrogats.</head>
                  <p>NO Chancellor, Commiſſary, Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, Officiall, or any other perſon vſing Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction, ſhall at any time ſubſtitute in their abſence any to keepe any Court for them, except hee bee either a graue Miniſter and a Graduate, or a licenſed publike Preacher, and a Beneficed man neere the place where the Courts are kept, or a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelor of Law, or a Maſter of Arts at leaſt, who hath ſome skill in the Ciuill and Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall Law, and is a fauourer of true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and a man of modeſt and honeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, vnder paine of Suſpenſion for euery time that they offend therein from the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Offices for the ſpace of three mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths <hi>Toties quoties.</hi> And hee likewiſe that is Deputed, being not qualified as is before ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and yet ſhall preſume to be a Subſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute
<pb facs="tcp:152063:153"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:154"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:154"/>
to any Iudge, and ſhall keepe any Court as is aforeſaid, ſhal vndergoe the ſame cenſure in maner and forme as is before expreſſed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>Proctors.</head>
               <div n="129" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXXIX.</hi> Proctors not to retaine Cauſes, without the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full aſsignement of the parties.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>One ſhall Procure in any cauſe whatſoeuer, vnleſſe he be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto conſtituted and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the partie himſelfe, either before the Iudge, and by Act in Court, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in the beginning of the Suit, hee be by a true and ſufficient Proxie thereunto warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and enabled. Wee call that Proxie ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, which is ſtrengthened and confirmed by ſome authenticall Seale, the parties approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or at leaſt his ratification therewithall concurring. All which Proxies ſhall be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with by the ſayd Proctors exhibited into the Court, and be ſafely kept and preſerued by the Regiſter in the publike Regiſtrie of the ſaide Court. And if any Regiſter or Proctor ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:152063:155"/>
offend herein, he ſhall bee ſecluded from the exerciſe of his Office for the ſpace of two mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths without hope of releaſe or reſtoring.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="130" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXXX.</hi> Proctors not to retaine Cauſes without the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of an Aduocate.</head>
                  <p>FOr leſſening and abridging the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Suits and contentions, as alſo for preuenting the complaints of Suiters in Courts Eccleſiaſticall, who many times are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowen by the ouerſight and negligence, or by the ignorance and inſufficiencie of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, and likewiſe for the furtherance and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of learning, and the aduancement of Ciuil and Canon Law, following the laudable cuſtomes heretofore obſerued in the Courts pertaining to the Archbiſhop of Canterbury, Wee will and ordaine, that no Proctor exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in any of them ſhall intertaine any Cauſe whatſoeuer, and keepe and retaine the ſame for two Court dayes, without the Counſell and aduiſe of an Aduocate, vnder paine of a yeeres ſuſpenſion from his practiſe: neither ſhall the Iudge haue power to releaſe or miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate
<pb facs="tcp:152063:155"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:156"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:156"/>
the ſaid penaltie, without expreſſe Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date and Authoritie from the Archbiſhop a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="131" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXXXI.</hi> Proctors not to conclude in any Cauſe, without the knowledge of an Aduocate.</head>
                  <p>NO Iudge in any of the ſaid Courts of the Archbiſhop, ſhall admit any Libell, or any other matter without the aduice of an Aduocate admitted to practiſe in the ſame Court, or without his ſubſcription: neither ſhall any Proctor conclude any cauſe depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, without the knowledge of the Aduocate retained and feed in the cauſe: which if any Proctor ſhall doe, or procure to bee done, or ſhall by any colour whatſoeuer defraud the Aduocate of his duetie or Fee, or ſhall be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in repairing to the Aduocate, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring his aduice what courſe is to bee taken in the cauſe, he ſhalbe ſuſpended from all pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe for the ſpace of ſixe moneths, without hope of being thereunto reſtored, before the ſaid terme be fully complete.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="132" type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:157"/>
                  <head>CXXXII. <hi>Proctors prohibited the oath</hi> In animam Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini ſui.</head>
                  <p>FOraſmuch as in the probate of Teſtaments and Suits for adminiſtration of the goods of perſons dying Inteſtate, the oath vſually taken by Proctors of Courts <hi>In animam conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuentis,</hi> is found to be inconuenient: Wee doe therefore decree &amp; ordaine, That euery Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor or Suitor for adminiſtration, ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally repaire to the Iudge in that behalfe, or his Surrogate, and in his owne perſon (and not by Proctor) take the oath accuſtomed in theſe caſes. But if by reaſon of ſickneſſe or age, or any other iuſt let or impediment, he be not able to make his perſonall appearance before the Iudge, it ſhall bee lawfull for the Iudge (there being faith firſt made by a credible per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, of the trueth of his ſaid hinderance or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment) to grant a Commiſsion to ſome graue Eccleſiaſticall perſon abiding neere the partie aforeſaid, whereby hee ſhall giue power and authoritie to the ſaid Eccleſiaſticall perſon in his ſtead, to miniſter the accuſtomed oath
<pb facs="tcp:152063:157"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:158"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:158"/>
aboue mentioned, to the Executor or Suitor for ſuch adminiſtration, requiring his ſaide Subſtitute, that by a faithfull and truſtie meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger hee certifie the ſayd Iudge truely and faithfully what he hath done therein. Laſtly, we ordaine and appoint, That no Iudge or Regiſter, ſhall in any wiſe receiue for the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, Drawing, or Sealing of any ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion, aboue the ſumme of ſixe ſhillings and eight pence: whereof one moitie to bee for the Iudge, and the other for the Regiſter of the ſaid Court.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="133" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXXXIII.</hi> Proctors not to be clamorous in Court.</head>
                  <p>FOraſmuch as it is found by experience, that the lowd and confuſed cries and cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of Proctors in the Courts of the Archbiſhop, are not onely troubleſome and offenſiue to the Iudges &amp; Aduocates, but alſo giue occaſion to the ſtanders by, of contempt and calumnie toward the Court it ſelfe: that more reſpect may be had to the dignity of the Iudge, then heretofore, and that cauſes may more eaſily and commodiouſly bee handled
<pb facs="tcp:152063:159"/>
and diſpatched, We charge and enioyne, That all Proctors in the ſaid Courts do eſpecially in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, that the Acts be faithfully entred and ſet downe by the Regiſter, according to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and direction of the Aduocate, that the ſaid Proctors refraine loude ſpeech, and brab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and behaue themſelues quietly and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly, and that when either the Iudges or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocates, or any of them, ſhal happen to ſpeake, they preſently be ſilent vpon paine of ſilencing for two whole Termes then immediatly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing euery ſuch offence of theirs. And if any of them ſhall the ſecond time offend herein, &amp; after due monition ſhall not reforme himſelfe: let him be for euer remoued from his practiſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Regiſters.</head>
               <div n="134" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXXXIIII.</hi> Abuſes to be reformed in Regiſters.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F any Regiſter, or his Deputie, or Subſtitute whatſoeuer, ſhall receiue any Certificate without the knowledge and conſent of the Iudge of the Court, or willingly omit to
<pb facs="tcp:152063:159"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:160"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:160"/>
cauſe any perſons cited to appeare vpon any Court day to be called, or vnduely put off, and deferre the Examination of witneſſes to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined by a day ſet &amp; aſsigned by the Iudge, or doe not obey and obſerue the iudiciall and lawfull monition of the ſaid Iudge, or omit to write, or cauſe to be written ſuch Citations and Decrees, as are to be put in execution and ſet foorth before the next Court day, or ſhall not cauſe all Teſtaments exhibited into his Office to bee Regiſtred within a conuenient time, or ſhall ſet downe or enact as decreed by the Iudge any thing falſe, or conceited by himſelfe, and not ſo ordered or decreed by the Iudge, or in the tranſmiſsion of Proceſſes to the Iudge <hi>Ad quem,</hi> ſhall adde, or inſert any falſehood or vntrueth, or omit any thing therein, either by cunning, or by groſſe negligence, or in cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Inſtance, or promoted of Office, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue any reward in fauour of either partie, or be of counſel directly or indirectly with either of the parties in Suite, or in the execution of their Office, ſhall doe ought elſe maliciouſly, or fraudulently, whereby the ſaid Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Iudge or his proceedings may be ſlandred
<pb facs="tcp:152063:161"/>
or defamed: We wil and ordaine that the ſaid Regiſter of his Deputie or Subſtitute, offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in all, or any of the premiſſes, ſhall by the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe be ſuſpended from the exerciſe of his Office, for the ſpace of one, two or three moneths, or more, according to the qualitie of his offence, and that the ſayde Biſhop ſhal aſsigne ſome other publike Nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to execute and diſcharge all things pertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to his Office, during the time of his ſayd Suſpenſion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="135" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXXXV.</hi> A certaine rate of Fees due to all Eccleſiaſticall Officers.</head>
                  <p>NO Biſhop, Suffragan, Chancellor, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſarie, Archdeacon, Officiall, nor any other exerciſing Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whatſoeuer, nor any Regiſter of any Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Courts, nor any Miniſter belonging to any of the ſaid Officers or Courts, ſhal here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after for any cauſe incident to their ſeueral Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, take or receiue any other or greater Fees, then ſuch as were certified to the moſt Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father in God <hi>Iohn</hi> late Archbiſhop of Canterburie, in the yeere of our Lord God,
<pb facs="tcp:152063:161"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:162"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:162"/>
one thouſand fiue hundred ninetie and ſeuen, and were by him ratified and approued, vnder paine that euery ſuch Iudge, Officer, or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter offending herein ſhall be ſuſpended from the exerciſe of their ſeuerall Offices, for the ſpace of ſixe moneths for euery ſuch offence. Alwayes prouided that if any queſtion ſhall ariſe concerning the certaintie of the ſaid Fees or any of them: then thoſe Fees ſhall be held for lawfull, which the Archbiſhop of Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie for the time being ſhall vnder his hand approoue, except the Statutes of this Realme before made, doe in any particular caſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe ſome other Fees to be due. Prouided furthermore, that no Fee or money ſhall bee receiued either by the Archbiſhop or any Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, or Suffragan, either directly or indirect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for admitting of any into ſacred Orders, nor that any other perſon or perſons vnder the ſaid Archbiſhop, Biſhop, or Suffragan, ſhall for Parchment, Writing, Waxe, Sealing, or any other reſpect thereunto appertaining, take aboue ten ſhillings, vnder ſuch paines as are already by Law preſcribed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="136" type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152063:163"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXXXVI.</hi> A Table of the Rates of Fees to bee ſet vp in Courts and Registries.</head>
                  <p>WE do likewiſe conſtitute and appoint, that the Regiſters belonging to euery ſuch Eccleſiaſticall Iudge, ſhall place two Tables, containing the ſeuerall Rates, and Summes of all the ſaid Fees: one in the vſuall place or Conſiſtorie where the Court is kept, and the other in his Regiſtrie, &amp; both of them in ſuch ſort, as euery man whom it concerneth may without difficultie come to the view and peruſall thereof, and take a Copie of them: the ſame Tables to be ſo ſet vp before the Feaſt of the Natiuitie next enſuing. And if any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter ſhall faile to place the ſaid Tables accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the tenor hereof, he ſhal be ſuſpended from the execution of his Office, vntil he cauſe the ſame to be accordingly done: and the ſaid Tables being once ſet vp, if hee ſhall at any time remooue or ſuffer the ſame to be remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, hidden, or any way hindered from ſight, contrary to the true meaning of this Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he ſhall for euery ſuch offence be ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:152063:163"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:164"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:164"/>
from the exerciſe of his Office for the ſpace of ſixe moneths.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="137" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXXXVII.</hi> The whole Fees for ſhewing letters of Orders, and other Licenſes due but once in euery Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops time.</head>
                  <p>FOraſmuch as a chiefe and principall cauſe and vſe of Viſitation is, that the Biſhop, Archdeacon, or other aſsigned to Viſite, may get ſome good knowledge of the State, Sufficiencie, and Abilitie of the Cleargie, and other perſons whom they are to Viſite: Wee thinke it conuenient that euery Parſon, Vicar, Curate, Schoolemaſter, or other perſon licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced whoſoeuer, doe at the Biſhops firſt Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, or at the next Viſitation after his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion, ſhew and exhibite vnto him his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Orders, Inſtitution, and Induction, and all other his Diſpenſations, Licences, or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties whatſoeuer, to bee by the ſaid Biſhop either allowed or (if there be iuſt cauſe) diſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed and reiected: and being by him appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, to be as the Cuſtome is, ſigned by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter, and that the whole Fees accuſtomed to
<pb facs="tcp:152063:165"/>
bee payed in the Viſitations in reſpect of the premiſſes, bee payed onely once in the whole time of euery Biſhop, and afterwards, but halfe of the ſaide accuſtomed Fees, in euery other Viſitation during the ſaid Biſhops con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Apparitors.</head>
               <div n="138" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXXXVIII.</hi> The number of Apparitors restrained.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as wee are deſirous to redreſſe ſuch abuſes and aggrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uances as are ſaide to grow by Sumners or Apparitors: Wee thinke it meete that the multitude of Appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors be (as much as is poſsible) abridged or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained. Wherefore we decree and ordaine, that no Biſhop or Archdeacon, or their Vicars or Officials, or other inferior Ordinaries, ſhall depute or haue more Apparitors to ſerue in their Iuriſdictions reſpectiuely, then either they or their predeceſſors were accuſtomed to haue thirtie yeeres before the publiſhing of
<pb facs="tcp:152063:165"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:166"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:166"/>
theſe our preſent Conſtitutions. All which Apparitors ſhall by themſelues faithfully exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute their Offices, neither ſhall they by any colour or pretence whatſoeuer cauſe or ſuffer their Mandats to be executed by any Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers or Subſtitutes, vnleſſe it bee vpon ſome good cauſe to be firſt knowen and approued by the Ordinarie of the place. Moreouer, they ſhall not take vpon them the office of Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters or Informers for the Court, neither ſhall they exact more or greater Fees then are in theſe our Conſtitutions formerly preſcribed. And if either the number of the Apparitors deputed ſhall exceed the foreſaid limitation, or any of the ſaide Apparitors ſhall offend in any of the premiſſes, the perſons deputing them, if they be Biſhops, ſhall vpon admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their ſuperiour diſcharge the perſons exceeding the number ſo limitted: if inferiour Ordinaries, they ſhall be ſuſpended from the execution of their Office vntill they haue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed the Apparitors by them ſo deputed, &amp; the parties themſelues ſo deputed ſhall for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be remooued from the Office of Appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors: and if being ſo remoued, they deſiſt not
<pb facs="tcp:152063:167"/>
from the exerciſe of their ſaid Offices, let them be puniſhed by Eccleſiaſticall cenſures as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons contumacious. Prouided, that if vpon experience the number of the ſaid Apparitors be too great in any Dioceſſe, in the iudgement of the Archbiſhop of Canterbury for the time being, they ſhall by him be ſo abridged, as hee ſhall thinke meete and conuenient.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Authoritie of Synodes.</head>
               <div n="139" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXXXIX.</hi> A Nationall Synode the Church repreſentatiue.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hoſoeuer ſhall hereafter af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that the Sacred Synode of this Nation in the Name of CHRIST, and by the Kings Authoritie aſſembled, is not the true Church
<pb facs="tcp:152063:167"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:168"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:152063:168"/>
of ENGLAND by repreſentation, let him be Excommunicated, and not reſtored, vntill hee repent and publikely reuoke that his wicked error.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="140" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXL.</hi> Synodes conclude as well the abſent as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</head>
                  <p>WHoſoeuer ſhall affirme, that no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of perſon either of the Clergie or Laitie, not being themſelues particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly aſſembled in the ſaid ſacred Synode, are to be ſubiect to the Decrees thereof in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall (made and ratified by the Kings Maieſties ſupreme Authoritie) as not hauing giuen their voices vnto them: let him bee Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated, and not reſtored vntill hee repent and publikely reuoke that his wicked error.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="141" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CXLI.</hi> Deprauers of the Synode, cenſured.</head>
                  <p>WHoſoeuer ſhall hereafter affirme, That the ſacred Synode aſſembled as aforeſaid, was a company of ſuch perſons as did conſpire together againſt god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Religious profeſſors of the Goſpel: and
<pb facs="tcp:152063:169"/>
that therefore both they and their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, in making of Canons and Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall by the Kings au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie as aforeſaid, ought to be deſpiſed and contemned, the ſame being ratified, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and enioyned by the ſaid Regall Power, Supremacie, and Authoritie: let them be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated and not reſtored, vntill they repent and publikely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke that wicked error.
<pb facs="tcp:152063:169"/>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:152063:170"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152063:170"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E of our prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> inclination, and Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all care for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the preſent Eſtate and Gouernement of the Church of <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> by the Lawes of this our Realme now ſetled and eſtabliſhed, hauing diligently, with great contentment and comfort, read and conſidered of all theſe their ſayd Canons, Orders, Ordinances, and Conſtitutions agreed vpon, as is before expreſſed; and finding the ſame ſuch, as Wee are perſwaded will bee very profitable, not onely to our Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, but to the whole Church of this our kingdome, and to all the true members of it, (if they be well obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) Haue therefore for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, our
<pb facs="tcp:152063:171"/>
Heires, and lawfull Succeſſours, of our eſpeciall Grace, certaine Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and meere Motion giuen, and by theſe preſents doe giue our Royall aſſent, according to the forme of the ſayd Statute or Acte of Parliament aforeſayd, to all and euery of the ſaid Canons, Orders, Ordinances, and Conſtitutions, and to all and euery thing in them contained, as they are before written.</p>
            <p>And furthermore, Wee doe not onely by our ſayd Prerogatiue Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and ſupreme Authoritie in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall, ratifie, confirme, and eſtabliſh by theſe our Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, the ſayd Canons, Orders, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and Conſtitutions, and all and euery thing in them contayned,
<pb facs="tcp:152063:171"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:172"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:172"/>
as is aforeſayd: but doe likewiſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, publiſh, and ſtraightly enioyne and command by our ſayd Authority, and by theſe our Letters Patents, the ſame to bee diligently obſerued, executed, and equally kept by all our louing Subiects of this our kingdome, both within the Prouince of <hi>CAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TERBVRIE</hi> and <hi>YORKE,</hi> in all points wherein they doe or may concerne euery or any of them, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this our will and pleaſure hereby ſignified and expreſſed: and <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> likewiſe for the better obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them, euery Miniſter, by what name or title ſoeuer he be called, ſhall in the Pariſh Church or Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell where he hath charge, reade all the ſayd Canons, Orders, Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="tcp:152063:173"/>
and Constitutions once euery yere, vpon ſome Sundayes or Holy dayes, in the afternoone before Diuine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, diuiding the ſame in ſuch ſort, as that the one halfe may bee read one day, and the other another day: the Booke of the ſayd Canons to be proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at the charge of the Pariſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt this and the Feast of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuity of our Lord God next enſuing: Straightly charging and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all Archbiſhops, Biſhops, and all other that exerciſe any Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Juriſdiction within this Realme, euery man in his place, to ſee, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure (ſo much as in them lieth) all and euery of the ſame Canons, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Ordinances and Constitutions to be in all poynts duely obſerued, not
<pb facs="tcp:152063:173"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:174"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:152063:174"/>
ſparing to execute the <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ena<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> them ſeuerally mentioned, vpon <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that ſhal wittingly or wilfully breake, or neglect to obſerue the ſame, as they tender the honour of God, the peace of the Church, the tranquilitie of the Kingdome, and their dueties and ſeruice to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s their King and Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In witneſſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:152063:175" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by ROBERT BARKER, Printer to the Kings moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>ANNO DOM. 1604.
<pb facs="tcp:152063:175"/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
